<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon Sir Henry Vanes book, entituled The retired mans meditations. Examining his doctrine concerning Adam's fall, Christs person, and sufferings, justification, common and special grace; and many other things in his book. / By Martin Finch, preacher of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1670_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867362</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867362</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119669</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119669)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1670[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon Sir Henry Vanes book, entituled The retired mans meditations. Examining his doctrine concerning Adam's fall, Christs person, and sufferings, justification, common and special grace; and many other things in his book. / By Martin Finch, preacher of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 179, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Barber, and are sold at the Lamb in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vane, Henry, --  Sir, 1612?-1662. --  Retired mans meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119669:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON Sir HENRY VANES Book, ENTITULED <hi>The Retired Mans Meditations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EXAMINING His Doctrine concerning <hi>Adam's Fall, Chriſts Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Juſtification, Common</hi> and <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace;</hi> And many other things in his Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Martin Finch, <hi>Preacher of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And they ſhall turn away their eares from the truth, and ſhall be turned unto Fables,
<bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 4.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Barber,</hi> and are ſold at the <hi>Lamb</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119669:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119669:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruths whatſoever are precious, as coming from a God of immenſe truth and goodneſs, and as tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deliverance of poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from the ſlavery wherein all are naturally held.</p>
            <p>The more clearly truth breaks forth and ſhines, the more doth the great Enemy <hi>who is a lyar, and the Father of lyes,</hi> oppoſe it.</p>
            <p>In ſhaking times nothing doth more diſcover a diſciple of Chriſt indeed, then <hi>continuing in Chriſts words;</hi> he hath promiſed that ſuch <hi>ſhall know the truth, and the truth ſhal make them free.</hi> We never had more need to put the promiſe in ſuit <hi>(ye ſhall know the truth)</hi> then at this day when ſo many ſtudy to darken it, <hi>and by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craftineſse lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all truths, thoſe about Juſtification are the moſt precious; and the leaſt diminution of that muſt needs wound the heart deep where it is clearly evidenced; that is indeed the Pearl; if that be ſafe, all is ſafe: Whether this be intrenched upon or no by the book that is here anſwered, the ſpiritual Reader can eaſily judge. The Gentleman is known to be a man of great honour, and of eminent parts; but
<pb facs="tcp:119669:3"/>truth is moſt honourable of all; all titles muſt ſtoop to it, and it will be juſtified againſt whomſoever by her children.</p>
            <p>The Anſwerer (though he have not follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Author from point to point, yet) hath cleared thoſe paſſages that ſeemed to be moſt dangerous, and yet without any gall or bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I dare ſay out of meer zeal to truth, having as high and honorable thoughts of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman oppoſed, as can conſiſt with ſincerity and uprightneſs of Chriſtian charity.</p>
            <p>The Lord keep us in the wayes of truth and peace, remove all heart-burnings and ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: Pride was the firſt ſin that brought us low, and keeps us low, and, I fear, the laſt that we ſhall conquer. The good Lord make us ſee our Emptineſs, help us to return all we have and are, to him that is the Fountain and God of all grace and glory, that he in all things may be glorified, and Chriſt be ſet up in his Royalty and Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Reader (If thou haſt any intereſt in him who is a God hearing prayers) pray for him who (though he be leſſe then the leaſt of all Gods mercies and ſervants, yet) delighteth more to be <hi>known of God by name, that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nsme,</hi> and to be in the hearts and pravers of his people by thouſands of degrees, then to be known upon any civil reſpect by his civil name.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT ALFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119669:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed this Noble Knight upon his retirment (after he had been ſuch a great bleſſing in publique affairs to the Nation) to ſet himſelf more cloſely then before to the ſtudy of Goſpel-myſteries, a thing little minded by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of the great ones, Knights and Nobles of this world; moſt of that rancke adicting themſelves to profaneſs and vanity, making uſe of the large portion that God hath given them under the Sun, to treaſure up more wrath againſt the day of wrath) It were well if others of his rancke and quality in the world, were provoked by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſtudy the <hi>excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> This Author hath not contented himſelf in the ſhallows, but hath waded into the deeps of Divinity, poſſibly ſo far ſometimes as that he cannot feel the ground of Scripture: Alas, the beſt are but men, and great parts and a ſwinge of reaſon are great temptations, unleſs <hi>our thoughts and reaſonings be brought into
<pb facs="tcp:119669:4"/>captivity to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it bath pleaſed God to leave this Noble Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in his ſerious enquiry into Goſpel-myſteries to much darkneſs, and many wide miſtakes in the great points of the Goſpel. The deſire of ſome godly friends, and the unſetledneſs of others in thoſe matters, being too much like <hi>little children, toſt to and fro with every wind of doctrine;</hi> with ſomething elſe that I ſhall not mention, put me upon theſe Animadverſions upon his Book, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which I ſhall deſire the Reader to take notice.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That I had no intent to have publiſhed theſe ſew ſheets if I could have ſeen it done by another; I finiſht what I have done in <hi>November</hi> laſt, and kept them by me, deſiring ſome other might do this work; which I had once ſome hopes of, but was afterwards enformed that it would not be; and ſo have now ſent them to the Preſs, in the ſame <hi>craſſo filo</hi> in which I firſt writ them; which I did at ſpare hours, in a months time.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> What I have written is not for the learned but for weak Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I have written but little of the Trinity, becauſe the Authors judgement is hard to find out about it, that I knew not where to have him; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is ſuch an inſcrutable myſtery that it is rather to be adored and believed then diſputed.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> I have endeavoured to be brief, becauſe books are ſo many (whereby men are hindred from
<pb facs="tcp:119669:4"/>reading of the Scriptures, for which cauſe <hi>Luther</hi> wiſht his books burnt) that if I wrote it ſhould be as little as might be.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> If thou ſeeſt me to be in the right, and this Noble Knight to be miſtaken &amp; in the darke, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cenſure him, nor deſpiſe his other gifts, but if thou beeſt godly pray for him, that wherein he is miſtaken <hi>and otherwaies minded</hi> from the truth and Saints of God, <hi>that God would reveal even that unto him,</hi> for ſurely he would welcome any light <hi>and would not turn aſide from the truth and flocks of Chriſts companions;</hi> the time is not yet come that the Saints ſhould be of one min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and judgement, the Lord haſten the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the gracious promiſes he hath made in that behalf, and grant that we may in the mean while wherein we differ be found ſpeaking the truth in love, <hi>Eph. 4.15.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Truthifying (as ſome render it) in love, and not in gall and bitterneſs, not ſeeking one anothers diſgrace and ſhame, but the finding out and maintaining the truth of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> If thon thinkeſt any paſſages unſeemly or any way reflecting upon that noble Author, Impute it to the haſtineſs of my writing, aſſuring thy ſelf it was not premeditated truly; I would not detract any way from his worth, whom I ſo ſeriouſly honour; but for writing plainly to my light and conſcience I beg no excuſe. And let the Reader conſider that theſe things which are here handled, are the main
<pb facs="tcp:119669:5"/>points of the Goſpel, the foundation of all our comfort and hope, <hi>the things by which we live, and in which is the life of our ſpirits; and therefore blame me not if I ſometime ſpeak plain Engliſh; its not againſt his perſon, but againſt his doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord make known his truth more perfectly, and eſtabliſh us in it, and grant that all our poor labours may tend to the advancement of it, and that we may neither ſpeak, nor write, <hi>nor do any thing againſt the truth, but all for the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Tetuey <date>
                     <hi>the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of he Month commonly called</hi> March <hi>1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>So prayes the Lords moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervant MARTIN FINCH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119669:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Concerning the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>the cauſe of his Fall, and of the Angells, the cauſe of their Fall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD made man righteous,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in his owne image, in reſpect of certaine divine excellencies and qualities he beſtowed upon him, placed him in the garden of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, was pleaſed to forbid him the eating of the <hi>tree of knowledge, nor to touch it, leſt he dye;</hi> this ſtate of happineſs that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was in, was mutable and uncertain, becauſe upon his diſobedience he forfeites all his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges annexed to his ſtate, and God never reſolved by his mighty power and over-ruling Spirit to keepe him from diſobedience, ſo that he ſtood a very little while in innocency, but by diſobeying God in eating of the forbidden fruit, fell from his firſt purity and holyneſs of minde, and openeth a wide doore <hi>for ſin to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the world, and death by ſin;</hi> this ſin of <hi>A-Adam</hi> had many aggravations, as he ſaid to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119669:6"/>
                  <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſirian,</hi> if the Prophet had bad thee do ſom great thing, wouldeſt thou not have don it? how much more, now he bids thee but waſh and be clean; ſo <hi>Adam,</hi> if thy Creator that made thee ſo noble and excellent, had required harder ſervice then ever he required of thee, wouldeſt thou, or ſhouldeſt thou have done it? and if he had forbidden thee al the trees of the garden but one, ſhouldeſt thou not have obeyed him in it? how much more when he forbiddeth thee but one tree among ſo many, wouldeſt thou not forbeare it? I might ſhew, if there were need, how this ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> was ſpiritual Idolatry, Adultery, and ingratitude towards that God that had done ſo much for him; having ſaid this by the way, let us examine what this Author ſaith of <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate before the fall, and how he fell.</p>
               <p>Page 67. [<hi>He ſaith, that God did not give</hi> Adam <hi>ſufficient grace and ſtrength to doe what he required and commanded, but it was</hi> Adams <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to thinke ſo.</hi>] But I anſwer, then his fall wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neceſſary, whether he would or no, even like our caſe, that have cauſe to complaine with <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>the evill which we would not do, that we do,</hi> for want of ſtrength to reſiſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſin and temptations to it, though it be quite againſt our will, and the deſire of our hearts, as to the inward man, according to which we delight in the Law of God, and would noe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119669:6"/>way offend him, but this would leſſen the ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> in diſobeying Gods commands, if he had not power and ability given him by God to do what God required of him, this impotency which we are ſenſible of, came by the fall, and was not before he, and we in him, loſt that divine excellency and ſtrength which God had beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him.</p>
               <p>Page 70. [<hi>He ſaith, that the frame of Spirit and minde, that God had in his eye, to bring upon Angells and men, ſtands in direct oppoſition and croſſe conſtitution, to what the Angells and</hi> Adam <hi>had at firſt.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Unleſſe the Author meanes here, that mens having life in the way of their own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; their having life by Chriſt and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſtand thus in direct oppoſition, I know not how, what he ſaith is true, and if he ſhould mean ſo, he ſhould not have put Angels and men together, for the Scripture tells us of no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that are juſtified by Chriſt blood, and made the righteouſneſs of God in him; but I thinke this is not his meaning, becauſe he doth not ſay, that the way of geting life in one ſtate, and another, were ſo differing, but he ſaith, the frame of Spirit and minde in the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtand in direct oppoſition; I know the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in Chriſts grace is in ſome things differing from <hi>Adams,</hi> as in cloſing with Chriſt by acts of faith, and ſeeing ſuch ſinfulneſs and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119669:7"/>in himſelfe, which <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate did not admit of, yet neither is this the meaning of the Anthor, neither is there ſuch a direct oppoſition, and croſſe conſtitution here, ſuch a frame of Spirit is as ſuitable to the believers ſtate, as <hi>Adams</hi> was to his, but ſurely he meanes that the higher Image, which he ſuppoſes is the unvailed glory of the Father, and this lower image, in which Angells and man were made at firſt, ſtands in direct oppoſition and croſſe conſtitution: now the Author makes the unvailed and original glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to be the witneſs of the firſt perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the ſtate of the Angels, and of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> to be the witneſs of the ſecond perſon in the Trinity; and do theſe ſtand in ſuch direct oppoſition and croſſe conſtitution? ſurely the operations of the bleſſed Trinity ſtands in the moſt compleat and perfect harmony, that this direct oppoſition is not in the operations of the perſons of the bleſſed Trinity, but in our either miſtaken or imperfect knowledge of them.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, he ſaith further:</p>
               <p>Page 54. <hi>[That on the Seventh day there was to be miniſtred to him a far higher and more exalted capacity of minde, for the enabling him unto an everlaſting, happy, and compleat communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Scripture ſaith nothing of this, that we muſt reject it, as being but mans conceit, <hi>Adam</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119669:7"/>was already in ſuch a ſtate, as he might have enjoyed ſuch happy communion with God, as God thought fit to communicate to him, while he obeyed him, and did his will in what here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, &amp; ſuch communion as was a high &amp; glorious priviledg, &amp; the Scripture ſaith not a word of any higher ſtate that God offered him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but there is one Scripture that the Author quotes for this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49. (he makes corruptible and mortall, to be meant as the ſtate wherein the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and immortality, to be meant of the higher Image which <hi>Adam</hi> was offered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, which he calls Chriſt in the Spirit, and Chriſt in his Heavenly appearances; Now that Scripture ſpeakes of the reſurrection, that we ſhall be made alive, and the corruptible ſhall put on incorruptability, and the mortall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, yea, the the very wicked ſhall never goe out of being (which would be a priviledge and mercy to them) but body and ſoule kept up in being, to beare the vengeance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eternall fire and wrath for ever; and ſo the Apoſtle goeth on to ſhew the difference betweene our bodies here, and in Heaven, how Spiritual they ſhall be there, our vile bodies changed into the likeneſs of Chriſts glorious bodie, as they are now in the likeneſs of the firſt <hi>Adams,</hi> now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, then Spirituall, now earthly, then Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, ſo that this place is nothing to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119669:8"/>but ſpeakes of the difference betweene the believer here, and in glory.</p>
               <p>Page 59. [<hi>He ſaith, that God gave</hi> Adam <hi>a ſight of the higher ſtate, that he ſhould have come up to, and forbad him to fix his eye upon things ſeene, there being a reſerve of unſeen things, as an induring ſubſtance to be imparted and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to him on the ſeventh day, but he ſaith,</hi> page 60. <hi>and in many other places, that through an inordinate cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and deſire in him, to keep in the ſtate wherein he was, and rejecting of that higher ſtate,</hi> Adam <hi>provoked God, and fell, and ſo alſo he ſaith,</hi> Page 75. <hi>That the Angells that fell, it was becauſe they refuſed to go into this high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtate.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scripture noe where ſaith that God offered <hi>Adam</hi> a higher ſtate, but only that the devill told him of a higher, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. that if they would eate of the forbidden fruit, they ſhould be as Gods.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I do not a little marvel, that the Author ſhould write, that God was pleaſed to forbid <hi>Adam</hi> to fix his eye where he was, but before the ſeventh day to tell him, there was a higher ſtate on that day to be propounded to him, doth the Scripture ſay any ſuch thing? how doth the Author come to know this, that God ſhould ſay thus and thus to <hi>Adam,</hi> when the Scripture makes no mention of any ſuch thing, let us be wise to ſobriety, and not above what is written.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119669:8"/>
               <p>And thirdly, where doth the Scripture ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> had ſuch an inordinate deſire to keepe in that ſtate where he was, but rather ſhewes us the contrary, that he would loſe and forfeit that bleſſed ſtate, and ſell it at ſo cheap a rate, as for to but eat of the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evill.</p>
               <p>Yea fourthly, that the refuſing of the higher Image and ſtate, was the cauſe of the fall of the Angells; is without booke too, as well as the reſt, and its very probable, that their pride in teaching after a higher life and ſtate, was the cauſe of their fall, and ſo 1 <hi>Timothy</hi> 3.6. and other places, ſeems to make pride the ſin and condemnation of the Angells that kept not their firſt eſtate, and are delivered into chaines of darkneſs, but I ſhall rather confeſſe my owne ignorance in ſuch things, then be wiſe above divine revelation, knowing that ſuch ſecret things belong to God, and revealed things (ſuch as God is pleaſed to make known to us in his word) to us, and to our children.</p>
               <p>And though the Author hath told us already that <hi>Adam</hi> was offered this higher life, union with Chriſt in his Heavenly appearances before his fall, and would not except of it, yet page 78. <hi>He tells us, that in all likelihood</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>were ſaved, and brought to that higher ſtate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fall, and they refuſed it out of ignorance before.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119669:9"/>
               <p>It is likely that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were ſaved through faith in Chriſt, the Scripture ſeemeth to hold forth ſo much, in that the Lord did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fall, ſo declare Chriſt to them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and whether their cloathing. <hi>v.</hi> 21. did not hold forth their cloathing with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, I am not certaine, in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things we muſt ſpeake doubtfully, but this I am ſure of, that the Scripture ſpeakes not of his coming into that ſtate which the Author cals the higher Image, but <hi>Page</hi> 333. the Author makes the refuſing Chriſt in his ſecond appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or the higher Image, to be the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt; and elſewhere ſheweth, that he meanes it of a wilfull and knowing refuſall of that higher ſtate, now I ſay, that if God did ſo forewarne <hi>Adam,</hi> that he ſhould not refuſe the higher ſtate, that he would propound to him on the ſeventh day, and gave him a ſight what it was (as we but now queſtioned the Author for affirming) the Author by his principles would make it very probable, if not plain, that <hi>Adam</hi> commited the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, becauſe then he had ſuch a vaſt knowledge and inſight into things, and upon ſuch a cleare knowledge of the excellency of ſuch a ſtate, would yet refuſe, it ſeemeth to have been a very wilfull act, but in that <hi>Page</hi> 333. he ſaith, that <hi>Adam</hi> refuſed it ignorantly, and the devill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly; but if it be true what the Author
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119669:9"/>ſaith, <hi>Page</hi> 59. that God before the ſeventh day gave him a ſight and proſpect of that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtate, it could not be done in ſuch ignorance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning the Perſon of Chriſt, his Bloody Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Sufferings, to reconcile us to God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe knowledge of Chriſt, and him crucified, being ſo excellent and neceſſary, that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Paul</hi> counted all things but loſs and dung in compariſon of it, let us ſet our hearts to know him, his perſon, his offices, his uſefulneſſe, preciouſneſſe, what he is, what he hath done and ſuffered for us poore ſinners, <hi>Who all like ſheep have gone aſtray, and turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquities of us all, and by his ſtripes we are healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is both God and man in one perſon, the brightneſſe of the Fathers glory, &amp; the expreſſe Image of his ſubſtance, he is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Soſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatoe,</hi> that Saviour that doth deliver from all evill, and is the Author of eternall ſalvation, he is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that propitiation for our ſins, expiates our ſinnes, attones God, and makes him propitious to ſinners, he is the bleſſed and eternall ſon of God that came into the world to ſave ſinners, and to reconcile them to God by the blood of his croſſe, <hi>that was made ſin for us, who himſelf knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</hi> Let us ſee then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119669:10"/>what this Author ſaith of his perſon and death, but firſt let me tell the reader, that I will not follow the Authors way in ſpeaking over and over the ſame things in variety of words, as concerning the perſon of Chriſt, and his being firſt in one Image, and then in another, he goeth over with that diſtinction of the three Images or ſtates where Chriſt comes forth, twelve times in the firſt fourty pages, and afterwards ſo often, that I left counting, but as neere as I can I ſhall at once examine his doctrine concerning the perſon of Chriſt, ſave that I will forbeare a curious prying into that incomprehenſible myſtery of the bleſſed Trinity, but rather leaving him to delight himſelfe in his owne notions about it, I ſhall cry out, O the Depths of that Myſtery! and confeſſe, that the knowledg of that great myſtery is too wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me, it is ſo deep, that I cannot ſearch it out, and ſhould as well as others, but more darken that myſtery by my words, neither would I pleaſe the itching deſire of any reader, by ſhewing my ſelfe wiſe above what is written, as <hi>Calvin</hi> treating upon ſuch great myſteries, in the 13. Chapter of the firſt booke of his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſaith, <hi>Quos oblectat ſpeculandio intemperies minime placandos ſuſcipio,</hi> he would not goe about to pleaſe thoſe who delight in ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo as not to be wiſe to ſobriety, no more ſhal I after this ſhort digreſſion; let us examine his doctrine concerning Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119669:10"/>
               <p>Page 2. [<hi>He maketh Chriſt to be the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of God, that is Immanent and eternally abiding in himſelfe, and as ſo, is unexpoſed to any creature diſcerning, and page</hi> 3. <hi>ſaith, in this communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is one with God, and is God, this is that, which up and downe his booke, he calls the higher Image, the glory of the Father, and the like, and yet he ſaith,</hi> Page 2. <hi>and elſewhere, that Chriſt thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is not to be taken for the ſecond perſon of the Trinity, but for the witneſs that is borne by all three.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Now promiſing this, that it hath beene the way of thoſe that have broached falſe doctrine in all ages, to hide and cloud their opinions, with ſubtil diſtinctions, I ask firſt, how Chriſt is God, but as he is the ſecond perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for he makes him God in this ſtate, and yet he ſaith, doth not here conſider him as the ſecond perſon in the Trinity. Secondly, I ask, how any witneſs of the Trinity is God, it is ſomthing from God, but is not God, for then we ſhall make ſo many Gods, as there are witneſſes (to uſe the Authors words) from the Trinity; one <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> was hammering out ſuch notions about Chriſt. But now our Author makes this higher Image, <hi>Page</hi> 12. to be the perſonal appearance which all the three perſons in the Trinity make in Chriſt, and if ſo, he muſt make Chriſt none of the three pervons in the Trinity, but only with <hi>Servetus,</hi> ſom appearance,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119669:11"/>Image and Idea from the Trinity: but to what purpoſe ſhould I follow the Author in theſe his deepe ſpeculations, it ſuffices us to know, that our bleſſed Redeemer is the fellow of the Lord of hoſts, God equal with the Father, though he was found in faſhion as a man, and humbled himſelfe unto death, even the death of the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>Page 2. <hi>He ſaith, Chriſt in a ſecond ſenſe is the Image of God, that proceeds out of his mouth, to tabernacle with the creature in a temporary miniſtration, and he ſaith,</hi> Page 4. <hi>that this is the witneſs of the ſecond perſon of the Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before he had made Chriſt in that firſt Image the perſonal appearance, &amp; witneſs of the three perſons of the Trinity, and now tells us of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Image wherein Chriſt is, and is the witneſs but of one of the perſons of the Trinity, but we take Chriſt to be the ſecond perſon in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not only ſome witneſs from him, and image that he exhibits to the creature, and the Author makes this the ſtate wherein the world have union and communion with Chriſt; which ſtate he, by the operation of the third perſon in in the Trinity, was perſwaded to offer up and exchange for the higher Image, and yet faith he, was in the higher Image firſt, ſuch divers and ſtrange doctrine we meet with in that hooke, if he was firſt in the higher Image, how could he offer up the lower Image to get into it?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119669:11"/>The Author quotes for theſe three Images and witneſſes of the Trinity, the 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are three that beare record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> But I hope that place doth not ſay it was the witneſs of the Father to bring forth Chriſt in one Image, and the witneſs of the word to bring forth Chriſt into another Image, and the holy Ghoſts witneſs to bring him into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but if we mind the eleventh verſe of that Chapter, we ſhall ſee what the record or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, This is the record, that God hath given to us eternall life, and this life is in his Son, that God hath choſen and appointed Chriſt, and none other, to be the Prince and the Saviour, to give repentance unto Iſrael, and forgiveneſs of ſinnes, neither is there life and ſalvation in any other; and therefore the Apoſtle, v. 10. charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe that believe not this record of God, concerning Chriſt, that in him is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and life, and will not come to him that they may have life, and be ſaved through him, I ſay, he there chargeth ſuch with making God a Lyar, by not believing the truth of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that the bleſſed, Trinity beare in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and ſo page 4. he quotes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. he ſaith, that Chriſt is there called, he that is, by way of diſtinction from himſelfe, conſidered as he that was in the witneſs of the Father, and he that is to come in the witneſs of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119669:12"/>
               <p>This Scripture ſurely is not a little wreſted, for the foregoing verſe ſpeaketh of Chriſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming, behold he cometh with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and I am <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> which ſhewes the eternity of the Son of God, which is, which was, &amp; which is to come, the Almighty which is now ſet downe at the right hand of the Majeſtie on high, which was found in faſhion as a man, and put to death in the fleſh, is to come the ſecond time without ſin to ſalvation, the ſame Lord Jeſus, that after he had purged our ſins, by the ſacrifice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, was taken up to Heaven, is to come againe, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Jude.</hi> 14.15. So that this Scripture will no way ſerve his purpoſe, nor beare his expoſition; beſides, his expoſition will be very inconſiſtent with his owne judgment, for he thinks Chriſt is now in the higher Image, brought into it by the third perſon in the Trinity, but if by Chriſt to come, ſhould be meant that Image and ſtate, Chriſt ſhould not be yet in it, but it were a thing yet to do.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee whether a third Scripture, which he quotes in many places, will favour his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9. <hi>And to make all men ſee what is the fellowſhip of the Myſtery, which from the beginning of the world lay hid in God, who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This place he ſuppoſeth holds forth the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Image, in which the Trinity brought forth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119669:12"/>Chriſt; let us therefore conſider what is meant by this Myſtery, which from the beginning of the world lay hid in God, and how God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle is there treating of the Gentiles, being partakers of the promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel, and of his being imployed of God to preach among them that unſearchable riches of Chriſts love, righteouſneſs and grace, and ſo to make more evident and plain what is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> fellowſhip or diſpenſation of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which from the begining of the world lay hid in God, which was, that he would by Jeſus Chriſt, the ſeed of the woman, break the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head, and ſave his Elect, among which there were not only Jewes by nature, but ſinners of the Gentiles, this myſtery of ſalvation by Chriſt Jeſus, from the beginning of the world, hath lain hid in God, that though ſomething of it was diſcovered to <hi>Adam, Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, yet as v. 3.4. &amp; 5. the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt in other ages was not made knowne to the ſons of men, that is, ſo fully and plainly as it is now revealed to the holy Apoſtles and Prophets by the ſpirit; and ſo <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.26.27. Its ſaid, this myſtery hath been hid from ages and generations, but now is made manifeſt to the Saints, to whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this myſtery, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles Chriſt was Preached and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119669:13"/>believed to he the hope of glory; ſo that this place is not meant of Chriſts being in the higher image, the image of God in originall and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as the Author would have it; and for the other words, that God created all things by Jeſus Chriſt, if we underſtand thoſe words ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the 1 <hi>John,</hi> that all things were made by the word, ſo that without him was not any thing made that was made, it will not make in the leaſt for the Authors ſecond image, but this place I take rather to be meant of the new creation ſpoken of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.24. that he ſaveth all his people, Jewes or Gentiles, and maketh them new creatures by Jeſus; but take it which way we will, it is true that God created all things by Jeſus Chriſt, but I ſay, I take it rather to be of the Spirituall creating, and ſo ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 2.10. we are Gods workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus to good workes, which God before ordained that we ſhould walke in them.</p>
               <p>Page 89. <hi>[He ſaith, that the death of Chriſt muſt not be confined to his offering up in the daies of his fleſh, but what he did then in a viſible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in mans nature, he did from all eternity, in an inviſible manner, in his Heavenly and myſticall ſtate.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27.28. will be againſt the Author do what he can, for it tells us Chriſt was once offered, that is, but once he ſpeakes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119669:13"/>excluſively; and ſee <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.27. that he did it at once; and ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. and ſaith v. 25. that Chriſt doth not offer himſelfe often, as the High-Prieſts of the law, that offered often, entring into the holy place every yeare, with the blood of others, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.11.12. By the which will we are ſanctified, through the offering of the body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all, that is, to offer himſelfe but once as a ſecrifice for our ſins, not like the High-Prieſts that ſtood daily Miniſtring and offering often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the ſame ſacrifice, but this man, after he had offered up one ſacrifice for ſins, for ever ſate down on the right hand of God; and <hi>v.</hi> 14. for by one offering, he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified: I know not how the holy Ghoſt could more plainly confute this Author, then in theſe words I have ſet downe out of that Epiſtle, doth this Author thinke that Chriſt from eternity was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, was crucified and put to death in the fleſh, and his ſoule made an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin, was bruiſed and put to greife; by Gods eternal decree and purpoſe, he was thus to ſuffer for our ſins, in the body prepared him, in the volume of Gods booke it was written of him, that he ſhould come thus to do the will of God, in ſuffering for our ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, and in the daies of his fleſh did ſuffer nothing but what God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119669:14"/>and afore determined, but Chriſt never died and ſuffered for our ſins, untill he was made fleſh, and dwelt among us, but I know what this Author means by Chriſts death, that is to ſay, his being broken, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the lower image, to goe up into the higher, the image of God in originall and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and thinketh this was from eternity, and that we ſhall examine in its proper place.</p>
               <p>The next thing we ſhall conſider, is what the Author ſaith.</p>
               <p>Page 77. [<hi>That they proclaime their ſhort-ſightedneſs into Chriſts fullneſs and rich grace:</hi> (I wonder who of us are not ſhort-fighted herein, as knowing, but in part, and ſeeing, as thorough a glaſſe darkly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.) <hi>That looke upon the Lord Jeſus, as an accidentall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion onely, that God had in reſerve, in caſe of the entrance and coming in of ſin, and ſaith, there was no other way whereby the creature could obtaine a ſure, ſafe, incorruptible and immorall life, but by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, who was from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining the right object of faith to Angells and men, if they would have received him on the ſeventh day, before the coming in of ſin.</hi>]</p>
               <p>This Author doth not very fairely lay downe the judgment of others in this buſineſs, for they from whom he differeth in this matter, doe hold, that God from all eternity did
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119669:14"/>purpoſe to ſave the elect by Chriſt, and that fall of man did not make any change in God, that he ſhould do any thing upon it, which he had not determined, and purpoſed from al eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to do, which counſel of his ſtood firme and conſtant, and the fall of man gives accaſion to the Lord, to ſhew what he eternally intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was to mignifie his rich and free grace, in ſaving his elect in ſuch a wonderfull way, of juſtice and mercy, as by ſending his onely begotten Son that we might live thorough him, laying our iniquities upon him, that by his ſtripes we might be healed, but yet he that thus eternally intended to make Chriſts ſoule an offering for ſin, decreed the fall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and to glorifie the riches of his mercy another way, that conſidering Gods decree and eternall counſell, it was impoſſible but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſhould fal, and ſo it is a vain and frivolous queſtion, whether Chriſt ſhould not have come, if he had not fallen, <hi>Servetus</hi> that we ſpoke of before, &amp; <hi>O ſtander,</hi> were of this opinion with this Author, that Chriſt ſhould have been incarnate, whether <hi>Adam</hi> had fallen or no; ſuch enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement unthankful men give to the glad tidings of the goſpel, that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſiuners, that inſtead of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the great &amp; ineſtimable love of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and coming to Jeſus the Mediator of the new Covenant, that they might have life, dore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119669:15"/>about queſtions, that inſtead, I ſay, of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for this great ſalvation, and looking up to Chriſt this brazen ſerpent, that they may be healed, fall a diſputing, that this brazen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſhould have beene ſet up, whether men had beene ſtung with the fiery ſerpents or no, but inſtead of their ſpeculation herein, let us ſay with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. this is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt came into the world to ſave <hi>ſinners,</hi> which we had never been, if we had not fallen, for God made man righteous; and <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.5. God ſent his ſon, made of a woman, made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, he was ſent to ſeeke and to ſave that which was loft, he came to call ſinners to repentance; he was ſet forth to be a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſins, thorough faith in his blood, with innumerable places of Scripture to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And we may very well in anſwer to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor affirm, that God, if it had ſeemed good in his ſight, could have given eternal life to <hi>Adam,</hi> and preſerved him to the Heavenly kingdome, in the ſtate wherein he created him; but he ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt from the beginning, was the right object of faith to Angells and men; but I anſwer, that the Lord Jeſus could not be ſo the object of faith to them, as he is to us, ſince the fall, for before that, they were whole, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the Phyſitian, could not come to Chriſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119669:15"/>the brazen ſerpent for healing, as thoſe that were ſtung with the fiery ſerpents, they could not come as loſt creatures, and weltring in their blood, to Chriſt, that they might have life, could not apply his blood to cleanſe them from ſin, when as yet they had not ſinned, nor any guile found in their mouthes, but if men, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of admiring the rich and great ſalvation brought to light through the glorious goſpel, will curiouſly pry into the ſtate of the Angells, and things which they have not ſeene, vainely puft up with a fleſhly minde, under the notion of a ſpiritual mind, &amp; will be contentious about theſe things, we have noe ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God, but leave them to flatter themſelves in their owne ſpeculations, deſiring our ſelves to he found thankfull to God, and admirers of his love, who when we were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, reconciled us unto himſelf by the blood of his ſon, and deſirous to give all diligence to make ſure our union and communion with him, the Lord our righteouſneſs, who when we were loſt, came to ſeek us, and to ſave us.</p>
               <p>Page 94. <hi>He ſaith, that Jeſus Chriſt was the ſurety and Mediator of both Teſtaments,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>sponſor</hi> is one that undertakes to pay anothers debt, &amp; that Jeſus Chriſt is ſaid to be the ſurety of the better Teſtament, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.22. which better Teſtament is the covenat of grace, not the covenant of workes, and he is ſurety of no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119669:16"/>other Teſtament but that, and according to the tenour of that covenant, he the ſurety payes our debts, to God the creditor, payes that which he never took, ſuffereth for our ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, to bring us to God, and ſo doth the holy Ghoſt diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1.1.7. Telling us, the Law was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt; and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.6. Chriſt hath obtained a more excellent miniſtry, by how much alſo he is the Mediator of a better cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (not of the old) which is eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes then <hi>Do this and live;</hi> and ſoe likewiſe <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.15. And for this cauſe he is the Mediator of the new Teſtament, that by meanes of death, for the redemption of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions under the firſt teſtament, they which were called might receive the promiſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal inheritance, &amp; ſo the believers under the old teſtament, by this Jeſus the Mediator of the new teſtament, being called, were juſtified, &amp; received the promiſe &amp; poſſeſſion of the eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as well as we; to name no more Scriptures where I might abound, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. And to Jeſus the Mediator of the new covenant, and to the blood of ſprinkling, making it a great part of the glory and excellency of the Goſpel diſpenſation, above that of the Law, that Jeſus is the Mediator of this covenant, which if they had been of the Authors mind, they might
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119669:16"/>have ſlighted, ſaying, that ſo he was of the other, but enough to ſhew the Authors miſtake in this particular.</p>
               <p>Page 69. <hi>[He ſaith, that Chriſt had an exerciſe of a new life ſet up in him, in a way of faith, by which he did not onely perform the righteouſneſs and obedience required of man by the Law or firſt covenant, but that alſo which is required of him by the new and ſecond Covenant.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the new life &amp; faith (as the author calleth it) that was ſet up in Chriſt, the author will give us accaſion to ſpeak afterwards, for he thinketh Chriſt had a new birth and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as we. In the mean while, this is not very clear, that Chriſt did performe that righteouſneſs &amp; obedience which is required of man by the new &amp; ſecond Covenant; the goſpel, or new Covenant, calls for Faith in Chriſt, repentance, thankfulneſs, mourning for ſin, I wis the Goſpel calls for theſe things, and if the author had ſaid Chriſt purchaſed theſe things for us, and all things the goſpel or new Covenant calls for, ſo that thoſe for whom he Purchaſed them, ſhall have them in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time beſtowed upon them, if he had ſaid thus, we ſhould have agreed with him, but to ſay, that Chriſt by a new life, and way of faith, performed all that the new Covenant or goſpells requires, will hardly goe downe with us; did Chriſt believe, repent, mourne for ſin?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119669:17"/>and we muſt note all this while, that the author doth not ſpeake this of Chriſts paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereby he performed the Fathers will, in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aring our ſins in his owne body upon the tree, but he ſpeakes of it as a part of his active obedience, neither doth the diſpute come in here, whether we are juſtified by both Chriſts active and paſſive obedience, but the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here, is only of the nature of Chriſts active obedience, whether therein he performed the obedience that the Goſpel or new Covenant requires, that is, did believe in a Saviour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and mourn for ſin, I wis Chriſt was no ſinnes, that he needed to believe in a Saviour, he was no ſinner, that he needed to mourn for his ſins, theſe are things no way ſuitable to the perſon of Chriſt to do, but ſuitable to us, who are to believe in him that juſtifies the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and to loath our ſelves for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and abominations, but we ſhall ſee by and by how he levels the Lord Jeſus, debaſes him, whom God hath ſo highly exalted, and given him a name above every name, and ſo he ſaith.</p>
               <p>Page 97. <hi>That Chriſt by bringing his fleſhly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into the coſſation and reſt, required by the law of the new Covenant, he attaines the end for which they were at firſt given him, arriving at that moſt neere and intimate communion with God, which onely by faith, or the exerciſe of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119669:17"/>a newneſs of life, and operation, can be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would faine know what fleſhly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples there were in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that the law of the new Covenant required to be laid downe, and brought into ceſſation, are theſe words of truth and ſoberneſs, concerning our bleſſed redeemer, God bleſſed for ever? that he had ſuch fleſhly principles in him, as the law of the new covenant required, ſhould be brought into ceſſation, truely we have other manner of thoughts of Chriſt the Lord, our righteouſneſs, and ſo the author tells us, that ceaſing from his fleſhly principles, he gets to neere and intimate communion with the Father; ſo then it ſeemeth he had not ſuch neere and intimate communion with the Father before, but we do believe that the very human nature of Chriſt, had of Chriſt, had alwaies very neer &amp; intimate communion with the Father, excepting the time when it pleaſed the Father to bruiſe him, and put him to grief, when he made his ſoule an offering for our ſins, then God hid his face from him, that made him cry out My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</p>
               <p>Page 97. <hi>He makes</hi> Abrahams <hi>offering up</hi> Iſaac, <hi>ſpoken of</hi> James 2. <hi>To hold forth his offering up the firſt image.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not ſay much to throw downe his expoſition of that place, but I ſhall onely ſay
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119669:18"/>this, that if that act of his were the throwing up of the firſt image, then it ſhould ſeeme <hi>Abraham</hi> had not offered it up before, and ſo according to the authors way, was not in a ſaving ſtate, which if it were needfull, might abundantly be confuted out of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Page 98. <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Abraham <hi>herein was but the type, or figure of Chriſt, who performed this in himſelf, and this act of obedience, being imputed to us, preſents us righteous, and without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lame before the Throne of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſurely if we will put an allegoricall ſenſe upon this paſſage of <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering up his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> they do better that make <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to repreſent God the Father herein, that offered his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> gave his <hi>Iſaac</hi> for a ſacrifice for our ſins, the beloved ſon in whom he was ſo well pleaſed; but this author makes Chriſt, both <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he makes <hi>Iſaac</hi> his fleſhly part, but I wold have the author follow his allegories a little better and wiſelier, not to plainly contradict the holy Ghoſt in his allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for <hi>Gal:</hi> 4. The holy ghoſt maketh <hi>Iſhmael</hi> to ſignifie the covenant of workes, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the covenant of grace, and <hi>verſe</hi> 28. <hi>So we, as</hi> Iſaac <hi>was, are the Children of the promiſe;</hi> ſo that when the holy ghoſt makes <hi>Iſaac</hi> to ſignifie the new covenant, the author is too bold to make him ſignifie the law, and the offering of him, to ſignifie the offering up of a legall ſtate.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119669:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo this author ſaith more plainly, Page</hi> 99. <hi>That Chriſt actually ſacrificed the true Iſaac,</hi> crucifiing in himſelfe the life of his fleſhly <hi>ſeed and legall principles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how he thwarts the holy ghoſt, who will have <hi>Iſaac</hi> to hold forth the new covenant, the free woman, <hi>the Ieruſalem that is</hi> above, and to hold forth thoſe that are borne after the ſpirit, in that 4. <hi>Galath.</hi> But this author will needs have <hi>Iſaac</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the fleſhly ſeed, and legall <hi>principles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 99. <hi>[He ſaith, that Chriſt and his whole ſeed enter into reſt by Faith.]</hi> But the author muſt have a care how he rank Chriſt and the Saints together, and liken them in believing, we come to him, that is, beleive in him, and ſo our troubled, weary, heavy laden ſouls enter into reſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. And there is no ſuch way in the world to get reſt for a weary ſoule, but by faith in Chriſt, applying his blood, which ſpeaketh better things then the blood of <hi>Abel;</hi> but how Chriſt needes to enter into reſt by faith, as we ſinfull creatures do, is a paradox; but as I ſaid before, he levels the Lord Jeſus, and mightily <hi>debaſes him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 103. <hi>He ſaith, that which in the firſt ſenſe Chriſts naturall man was a ſufferer in, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the weakneſs and diſabilitie which was brought upon his</hi> fleſhly <hi>mind, to reſiſt the powerfull workings of his faith, or spirituall minde.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119669:19"/>
               <p>A ſtrange paſſage, that Chriſt had a fleſhly carnall minde in him, as well as a ſpirituall minde, but we believe there was no fleſhly mind in our Redeemer, and wonder that this author is ſo bold as to affirme it, and he maketh it the worke of his death and croſs, to ſubdue his fleſhly minde, and if there were ſuch a fleſhly mind in Chriſt Jeſus, it was no ſuffering and affliction to have that taken away, but rather a great mercy; but far be it from us to have ſuch low, and mean, and baſe thoughts of our deare Saviour.</p>
               <p>But in the ſame 103. Page <hi>[He ſaith, that Chriſt was thus brought into ſuch a frame of ſpirit. that he was diſabled from doing any thing againſt the truth, and thereby qualified to do all for the truth.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if there was a time when Chriſt had ſuch a frame of ſpirit, that he might have acted againſt the truth and will of God, but by taking up the higher image, was diſinabled from doing ſo, and before that time, was not qualified to do all things for the truth; and he adds in the ſame place, that this profitable weakneſs and diſability, (namely, not to do any thing againſt the truth) came not all at once upon Chriſts naturall man, but gradually; then this author would make him for a time to be in great danger of ſinning, but that by degrees he grew diſinabled from ſinning.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119669:19"/>
               <p>And Page 104. <hi>He ſaith, thus in this firſt part of Chriſts paſſive obedience, he through the law, becomes dead to the law, through the law of the ſpirit of life in the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>becomes dead to the law and life of the firſt, fulfilling the whole law of righteouſneſs, by being rendred utterly unable to perform one tittle of it in mans firſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and ſufficiency, or as left alone to the grace &amp; ſtrength received by his firſt covenant principles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us examine how Chriſt by the law, became dead to the law, <hi>Paul</hi> indeed ſaith thus of himſelfe. <hi>Gal</hi> 2.19. I through the law, am dead to the law, that is, ſeeing the law, ſpirituality, and my owne weakneſs to keep it, that if I be under the law, I muſt needs be under the curſe. I am dead to the law, that is, will not put my ſelfe under it, as a covenant of workes, to doe it and live, but I ſeeke to have my life hid with Chriſt in God, and to have him to be the end of the law for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to me; but Chriſt could not be dead to the law in this reſpect, for he was able to performe every tittle of it, which <hi>Paul</hi> and we were not able to doe; but I ſay, Chriſt needed not, as we, to fly from the law, as that which is weake, and unable through the fleſh, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in us, to keep it, to bring us unto life, and ſo to goe unto another for righteouſneſs and life; and he goes on, to make Chriſt one while keeping the law out of ſtrength that he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119669:20"/>received by firſt Covernant principles, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he faith, he could not performe one tittle of it, as left to thoſe principles, thus doth he repreſent Chriſt, one while obeying upon the principles of the Covenant of works, &amp; another while he could not obey at upon theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, running into theſe notions about Chriſt, by ſlighting the ſimplicity of the goſpel, which is, that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, &amp; that he by the appointment of God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Covenant between him and the Father, as our ſurety, performed the whole will of God, in that body prepared him to purge away our ſins, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, and the principles upon which he acted, were out of obedience to the Father, and love to ſinners, to compaſs the bleſſed deſigne of God, his glory, and our eternall ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Page 111. He goes about to ſhew what was the nature of that wrath from God, that Chriſt was capable of undergoing, which to make out, he defineth the wrath of God, <hi>thus ſaith he, wrath, as God is capable of exerciſing it, conſiſts in that poſture of an enemy, and face of displeaſure, wherewith he cloaths and armes himſelfe in Chriſt, the Mediator to Angels or men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſtrange definition of Gods wrath, for if it were ſo, that God is not capable of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wrath to Angels or men, but as he cloaths
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119669:20"/>and armes himſelfe to do it through Chriſt, then I ſay it will follow, that God could not have reſerved any of the Angels in chaines of darkneſs to the judgement of the great day, nor could not have damned any of the ſons and daughters of men, if Jeſus Chriſt had not been Mediator, ſurely the Reader will wonder at this notion of the Authors, and he doth not ſay, that God doth exerciſe wrath in Chriſt, or thorough Chriſt, as if he had meant that God was the moſt provoked to wrath for ſlighting Chriſt, and neglecting ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will execute the fierceneſſe of his wrath upon thoſe that trample under foot the blood of the Son of God; but he ſaith, that God is capable of exerciſing wrath no other way, but as he cloaths and arms himſelf in the Mediator, God is ſaid to be angry and wrath, when in his dealings with the creature, he walks contrary to him, and ſets himſelf againſt him; ſuppoſe it be eternal wrath, then God dawns that creature, and turneth him into hell, and doth the Author think that God could not have done thus, if Chriſt had never been a Mediator between God and us, could not God have exerciſed wrath upon all of us that are the fallen ſons of men, and appointed us our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the dark nooks of hell, without CHriſt had been the Mediator? and this Author will make Chriſt neceſſary to be the Mediator and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119669:21"/>Saviour upon this account, that elſe God could not have exerciſed wrath upon any of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>But I pray how could Chriſt bear the wrath of God, if that it be true that the Author ſaith, that God is not capable of exerciſing wrath, but in Chriſt the Mediator; well, we unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, inſtead of admiring the Lords free mercy in Chriſt, whereby we are delivered from wrath to come, who hath attoned God, made peace, and reconciled us to God; we fall a diſputing, that God is not capable of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing wrath, but thorough Chriſt the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator; but if it had not pleaſed the God of all grace to have ſent his bleſſed Son to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wrath from us, and reconcile us to himſelf, we ſhould have ſeen to purpoſe, and by lamentable experience, that God could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe wrath without Chriſt the Mediator.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119669:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Shews, that the higheſt attainments of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man come very far ſhort of what this Author aſſignes to him, and proves his miſinterpreting abundance of Scripture about this matter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS this Author doth exceedingly debaſe Chriſt, marring his viſage, who is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovely, often ſaying, he had a fleſhly mind, and fleſhly principles, which were to be ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him; ſo on the other hand, he cries up the natural mans attainments far above that which any natural man ever arrives at, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed takes the moſt of the Characters of a true Believer, and claps them upon a natural man.</p>
               <p>And ſo page 117. <hi>That Chriſt may be the received Lord and Chriſt in the heart, and give a participation and fellowſhip with him in ſpirit, by the power and preſence of himſelf there, either in his firſt or ſecond appearance, and all along he maketh the receiving of Chriſt in his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance only, to be no ſaving ſtate; and yet he ſaith in this ſtate, Chriſt may be the received Lord and Chriſt in the heart, and give the ſoul a participation and fellowſhip with himſelfe in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how plainly doth the Holy Ghoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute him, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>That to as many as receive him, to them gave he power to become the ſons of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119669:22"/>God;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>If ſons, then heirs, heirs of God, and coheirs with Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> So that whereſoever Chriſt becomes the received Lord and Chriſt in the heart, eternal ſalvation at that very time is come to that ſoul, foraſmuch as he is made the child of God by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, or by receiving Chriſt, which are all one, as that 1 <hi>John</hi> 12. makes plain, yea, this Author ſaith, that ſuch a ſoule Chriſt gives a participation and fellowſhip with himſelfe in ſpirit, but then is not this ſoul in a ſafe and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtate, for Chriſt to give a ſoul fellowſhip with himſelf in the fathers love, to make him a ſharer in his death, blood, and righteouſneſs, and ſpirit, and he that is thus called into fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Jeſus Chriſt, is ſurely in a ſaving ſtate; and by the way I would note this to the Reader, that whereas now the Goſpel is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more then in former ages, ſo that many places, and poor ſouls that have ſat in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſee a great deal of light that way, and men are told much of Chriſts being the way, the truth, and the life, and are earneſtly preſſed and invited to receive Chriſt that they might have life, it's now one of the devils grand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, to make men believe, that men may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt, and have fellowſhip, union, and communion with him, and yet not be in a ſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate, but be under the Covenant of works all this while, thinking if this doctrine would
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119669:22"/>take, it would keep thouſands from Chriſt, therefore it concerneth us to way lay his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and unmask him that transforms himſelf into an Angel of light, that under pretence of carrying us higher, would beguile us of the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, the ſure way of life and ſalvation, by receiving of Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord our righteouſneſs, and truly for ought I know, this Author is the firſt that ever broacht this doctrine in print, that a man might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Jeſus Chriſt, and have fellowſhip with him in ſpirit, and be made the righteouſneſs of God in him, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate; for the <hi>Arminians</hi> never had the face to ſay it was not a ſaving ſtate if they continued in it: Let us examine the Scripture he quotes, one is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. the beginning of that chap, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the fourth ver. that the Jews did all eat of the ſame ſpirituall meate that was Manna, our fathers did eate Manna in the wilderneſs, that Spirituall food, the unbeleevers among them eat that food, the true Beleevers eate the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Manna, and lived for ever, and it followeth that they all dranke of that Spirituall Rock that followed, and that Rock was Chriſt, but what is the meaning of it, but that they drank all of the Rock that is Spoken of <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.9. which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmote, and water came out, that they might all drink, which Rock was Chriſt, that is, a type of Chriſt, the rock of ages, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119669:23"/>being for the tranſgreſſions of Gods people ſmitten and bruiſed by the Father, from him cometh living waters, ſpringing up to eternal life; ſo that this place holdeth forth this only, that all the Jews did drink of the water of that Rock which was a type of Chriſt, and this will not do him any ſervice to make out his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Another Scripture he quotes, is <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.32. That my Covenant they brake, though I was an husband to them; that is, I ſhewed a great deal of kindneſs to them, and made a way thorough the Red Sea for them, leading them thorough the deep, as a horſe in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they ſhould not ſtumble, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, they ſoone forgot his works, and quickly turned aſide out of the right way, and walked contrary to him, and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him with their iniquities and abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and therefore God ſpeaketh of a better Covenant that he maketh with the ſpiritual <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> that is, to write his Laws in their hearts, and put his fear into their hearts, which they never had done for them who were the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers among the Jewes, neither did they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt into their hearts as Lord and Chriſt, which is the thing in queſtion; and <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.8.9, 10. which he quotes, holds forth the ſame, even the great deliverances that the God of ſalvations wrought for the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> when he led them by the right hand of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119669:23"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> with his glorious arme, dividing the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before them, to make himſelf an everlaſting name; but this place holdeth forth nothing of the Authors doctrine, that they had all recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt into their hearts, to be their Lord and Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. He quotes often for theſe things, becauſe its there ſaid, that when they lay in their blood, God ſaid unto them live, and made them perfect through the comelineſs put upon them, which he ſaith was the comelineſs and righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and yet they and God parted, and he became their enemy.</p>
               <p>But let us well weigh the 16. of <hi>Ezek.</hi> The Lord is there declaring what he had done for the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they lay in their blood; and as <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.14. Their lives were made bitter to them with hard bondage, and then God heard their groaning, and God had reſpect to them, he heard their cry, and knew their ſorrows; and ſo in this place of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the low and helpleſs condition of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is compared to a poor infant newly born; but ver. 14. God did ſo much for them, that they proſpered, into a Kingdom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great and glorious Nation, that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were now growne to be like the ſand of the Sea ſhore, innumerable, ſo that he ſaith, ver. 14. that their renown went forth among the Heathen for their beauty, that is,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119669:24"/>that the heathen took notice of their ſtrength and glory, and that God had done great things for them, ſo that many of them ſought to make league with them, for they were perfect through the comelineſs that he had put upon them, he had given them glory above all the Kingdomes of the earth, Statutes and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Lawes and righteous Judgments, he had not dealt ſo with any Nation as he had done for them. Now when we make uſe of theſe paſſages in this Chapter to hold forth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, Chriſts righteouſneſs, and ſuch things, then we muſt be careful of not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the true litteral ſenſe of them, and when we take it in a ſpiritual ſenſe, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe things of the body of the Jewes, then it is eaſily detected to be a wreſting of the words, to ſay all the Jewes had ſpititual life by Chriſt, and had his righteouſneſs and comelineſs put upon them, we have ſeen the meaning is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; but this we muſt underſtand, that thoſe things that are litterally ſpoken of the whole body of the Jewes, are ſpiritually only to be applied to the people of God, Jewes or Gentiles, for many of this people of the Jewes were ſo far from having ſuch an union with Chriſt, and were ſo far from ſuch a ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he ſaith men have by union with Chriſt in the fleſh, that they were Idolaters, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, and their lives worſe then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119669:24"/>and whoſoever ſhall read out this 16 Chap. of <hi>Ezek.</hi> ſhall ſee how wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly this Nation of the Jews were.</p>
               <p>They committed ſpiritual fornication, they joyned themſelves to idolatrous Nations, verſe 15. adorned the high places and Temples of their Idols, ver. 16. God had given them plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of gold and ſilver, and they made images and idols of it, ver. 18. and ſet his oyl and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe that ſhould have been uſed about his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, uſed them about their Idols, ver. 18. and ſo he goeth on to ſhew the wickedneſs of this people; and will this Author, or any man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecond thoughts think, that ſuch men as theſe have union with Chriſt, and have received him into their hearts as their Lord and Chriſt, and have his comelineſs and righteouſneſs put upon them.</p>
               <p>The Author goes on, page 118. ſaith he, <hi>It is evident then, that upon ſuch conditional termes as are comprehended in the tenour of the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Chriſt can, and doth cauſe his own recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the hearts and conſciences of men, and that there are inſeparable benefits attending and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying this manner of reception or believing in Chriſt, which is begotten, and held but upon the wavering principles of the firſt Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author had laid down his judgement, and quoted four Scriptures for it, and not ſo much as tells us how he would argue from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119669:25"/>them, which Scriptures we have taken the pains to weigh, and finde that they do not prove any thing for his purpoſe; and now without any more to do, the Author tells us, it is evident; tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if he makes it no more evident then he hath don yet, he wil fail mightily in his undertaking; but what is it he hath made ſo evident? why, that Chriſt can, and doth cauſe men to receive him upon the conditional terms of the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and what were the conditional terms of the firſt Covenant, but do this, and live? and doth Chriſt bring men to believe in him, and caſt anchor in their ſtorm upon his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and blood upon the terms of the old Covenant, <hi>Keep the Law, and ye ſhall live?</hi> no ſurely, but upon the terms of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Believe, and ye ſhall live, come to Chriſt, and ye ſhall have life:</hi> But let us hear what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits the ſoul hath that receives Chriſt in this way, though he will not have the ſoul to be in a ſaving ſtate here, yet ſaith, there are three benefits ſuch a ſoul hath.</p>
               <p>He ſaith in that 118. page, he ſaith firſt, <hi>They that are thus made receivers of Chriſt, are called out of the world, to come out of that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſtate wherein men live, as without Chriſt, and without God in the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly this is a great benefit, and ſurely who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is truly called out of the world, is in a ſaving ſtate, to be called out of the worlds pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119669:25"/>hypocriſie, will-worſhip, formality, called out of the worlds way, in going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, and living to themſelves and their luſts, I think a ſoul that is thus called out of the world, is in a happy condition, whatſoever this Author ſaith; for being by Chriſt called out of the world, he ſhall not be condemned with the world, and I am ſure Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 15.19. makes a mans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the world to be a natural man, and his being not of the world to be a ſtate of true Saintſhip, ſuch as the Diſciples themſelves had; and ſo if we conſider what it is to live without Chriſt, to wit, to live without the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the ſpirit, the grace, the faith of Chriſt, we may well ſay, that a man that Chriſt hath truly called out of a ſtate of living thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, is in a ſaving ſtate, for it muſt needs follow, that he being called out of a ſtate of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with Chriſt, he muſt needs now have Chriſt his righteouſneſs, his ſpirit, his grace. But the Author will grant us, that a man may have Chriſt his righteouſneſs and ſpirit, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For in the ſame</hi> 118. <hi>page, he cometh to ſhew a ſecond benefit which thoſe receive from Chriſt, that receive him in the firſt Covenant, he ſaith, Chriſt is made unto ſuch righteouſneſs in a way of juſtification, and they are made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in him, and that he affords ſuch the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119669:26"/>benefit of his legal righteouſneſs, ſo that the Law hath nothing to ſay againſt ſuch; and page</hi> 119. <hi>he ſaith, this juſtification the world hath in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with true Believers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think this opinion may call this Author fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for I think he is the firſt that ever affirmed (I mean one that went for a Chriſtian) that to be made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt, was not a ſaving ſtate; and truly we may ſay in this caſe as he ſaid, <hi>if I am bereaved, I am bereaved,</hi> if to be made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt doth not ſave us eternally, then we are bereaved indeed, and are of all men moſt miſerable, and the generation of Gods children the moſt deceived that ever any were in the world; but this Author muſt not think to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it thus, let us ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.5.9. <hi>Paul</hi> counted all things but droſs that he might win Chriſt, and be found in him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on him his own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith, and doth any man think that this was not a ſaving ſtate? and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>He hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> And is not this a certain and unfailing way to bring us to eternal life, to be made the righteouſneſs of God in him the Lord our righteouſneſs? hath God appointed any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119669:26"/>way to juſtifie ſinners, and bring them to eternal life and glory, then by being made the righteouſneſs of God in him, when God out of his rich grace maketh a poor ſinner accepted in the beloved, righteous in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, what ſhould hinder his ſalvation for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? who ſhould lay any thing to ſuch a ſouls charge to condemn him, when God juſtifies him through Chriſts righteouſneſs? and the Author here confeſſes, that the Law hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay againſt ſuch, when a ſoul can truly ſay by faith, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45.24. Though I have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, yet Chriſt Jeſus was made ſin for me, that I might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him; and ſurely in him have I righteouſneſſe, life, and ſtrength, that ſoul is in a ſaving ſtate, and ſhall never come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life, let all the devils in hell ſay what they will to the contrary; and though theſe places that I have already named be ſufficient to prove that which I am about, yet I ſhall name another that is as full as we can deſire, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. <hi>For if by one mans of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence death reigned by one, much more they that receive abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteouſneſs, ſhall reigne in life by one Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Let us mind this bleſſed Scripture, ſo full of marrow and fatneſs to feed our ſoules, <hi>If,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>by one mans offence death
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119669:27"/>reigned by one,</hi> that is, if by the one man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> offence, or his one offence of eating the forbidden fruit death reigned thereby, that is, we were all brought to death and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that his diſobedience being imputed to us, we were brought to ſuch miſery and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>much more they that receive abundance of grace, the grace of God which bringeth ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of the gift of righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, Chriſts righteouſneſs, to have that imputed to them, <hi>they ſhall reign in life by one Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that is as certainly as death and condemnation came upon us by <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience, ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſhall we have ſalvation, and reign in life and glory for ever, receiving the gift of Chriſts righteouſneſs, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and this is more explained in the 21. verſe of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>That as ſin hath reigned unto death, even ſo might grace reign thorough righteouſneſs unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, thorough Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> which plainly affirms this, that as <hi>Adams</hi> ſin brings eternal death and condemnation, ſo the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt brings eternal life and ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee whether he be not as much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the third benefit by Chriſt, that men may have, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate.</p>
               <p>Page 119. he ſaith, <hi>The third benefit inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably accompanying this kind of Chriſts giving himſelf by the firſt Covenant, is that which we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119669:27"/>call ſanctification,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30. <hi>conſiſting in a real and actual change of the heart, which lyeth in our conformity to Chriſts legal righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That place 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. ſaith, Chriſt is made of God unto us ſanctification and redemption, <hi>unto us,</hi> that is <hi>unto us</hi> that truly believe in him, but he doth not ſay that he is made ſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; what doth he mean by this real and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual change of the heart? doth he mean that which is called a new heart, and a new ſpirit, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. if ſo, he is out, for that onely God giveth to thoſe that are eternally ſaved; and truly methinks, that men inſtead of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that the natural man may be ſanctified ſo as to have new hearts, ſhould rather queſtion whether they themſelves be ſo ſanctified, and their hearts ſo really and actually changed, as to have new hearts and ſpirits, and when we come to examine this very thing, we ſhall finde that it is not ſuch an ordinarie thing to have the heart, which by nature is ſo deſperately wicked, to be ſo really and actually changed, though the life may be much changed, yet the heart may be the ſame, even like a painted Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, beautiful without, but within full of dead mens bones; but for this he maketh uſe of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. of mens eſcaping the polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world, through the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who yet may be againe intangled in them.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119669:28"/>
               <p>But doth the Author know no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween mens hearing of Chriſts calling for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and departing from iniquity, in the preaching of the Goſpel, that they do now leave their former prophaneneſs and polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hoping to get heaven, or make themſelves worthy of Chriſt by this their reformation, I ſay, is there no difference between this, and the having of the heart really and actually change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe <hi>Herod</hi> did many things, and heard <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gladly, doth it therefore follow, that he was ſo ſanctified, as to have his heart really and actually changed and purified, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. the heart is purified only by true faith in Chriſt Jeſus, the life may be reformed by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, by convictions of conſcience, and by a common head, and notional knowledg of the Goſpel, and of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; yet I confeſs in a good ſenſe, the hearts of ſome natural men may be ſaid to be change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but it muſt be very warily underſtood.</p>
               <p>Another place he quotes for this attainment of the matural man, is <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. Thoſe that taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the heavenly gift, and yet might fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>What if theſe are ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, ſo was <hi>Balaam,</hi> and others, that I hope were never juſtified and ſanctified by Chriſt, we do not deny but that the natural man may have illumination; what if they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119669:28"/>ſaid to have taſted of the heavenly gift, and if this heavenly gift be Chriſt himſelfe, men may taſt of Chriſt, as Cooks do of their ſauce which they ſpit out again; men may come to try Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and taſt Chriſt, and not having a pallat that ſavours the things of the ſpirit, may not like him: there is a great difference betweene the unbelievers taſting; and the true believers experience; what if they are ſaid to be made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, that may be ſaid of any man that is any way enlightened by the Holy Ghoſt, and partakers of his common gifts only, yea, <hi>Bezaliel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> are ſaid to be filled with the Spirit of God, when yet it was but to enable them to deviſe cunning works, in gold, and in ſilver, and in braſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.3.4.</p>
               <p>What if they taſted of the good Word of God, I queſtion not but a natural man may do ſo, as <hi>Herod</hi> that heard <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gladly, which ſhewed he was affected with the word, and taſted ſome ſweetneſſe in it.</p>
               <p>And what if they taſted the powers of the world to come, and have often been ſcared, as <hi>Felix</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. when <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned of the Judgement to come, <hi>Felix</hi> trembled, and ſo may other natural men do; but doth this Scripture ſay as the Author doth, that they received Chriſt in their hearts, as their Lord and Chriſt, and were made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119669:29"/>of God in him, this is the thing that we deny any natural man attaines to, but we grant they may taſt of the heavenly gift, and of the powers of the world to come, as that place in the 6. <hi>Hebr.</hi> doth declare.</p>
               <p>Page 134. he ſaith, <hi>Theſe in the firſt Image are righteous workers, according to the Law, in the moſt Goſpel adminiſtration of it, but at the bottome, are ſtill upon the tenure and account of debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the moſt Goſpel like adminiſtration of the Law, but Chriſts fulfilling of it for us, and taking the Law now into his own hands, and preſcribing the obedience the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, as duty to him the Lord our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that there is a modification of the Law to the fallen eſtate of man, that Chriſt now doth not propound the Law to us as a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works, that we ſhould ſeek righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to juſtifie us by the works of the Law, but he himſelf is made of God unto us righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and his blood cleanſeth us from all ſin, and now will have us obey the Law, as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits it to us in the way of the Goſpel, that we ſhould now obey out of love, thankfulneſſe, and obedience to our Redeemer, and this is the Goſpel, and Chriſts adminiſtration of the Law; but this Author tells us, that all the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome they are upon the account and tenure of debt, and that they are but ſtill under the firſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119669:29"/>Covenant, which is a meer contradiction; for the obeying of the Law in the moſt Goſpel like adminiſtration of it, implyes a diſclaiming our own righteouſneſſe and confidence in our owne obedience, and obeying it upon Goſpel princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, even our love and duty to Chriſt that conſtraineth us to do his will, and what is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in his ſight; and I would ask the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, whether thoſe that came into his higher image, are not to obey the Law, and if ſo, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will ſay they muſt obey it in the moſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel like adminiſtration of it, and then the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of them both are alike, the confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Law and Goſpel doth a little hang in this Authors light.</p>
               <p>Page 136. [He ſaith, <hi>This ſort of men were incorporated with the true ſpiritual ſeed, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the ſeven Churches mentioned,</hi> Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Chapters.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I pray were the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> that were neither hot nor cold, that ſaid they had need of nothing, and knew not they were miſerable, and poor and blind, and naked, did this frame of ſpirit ſhew them to be made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in Chriſt, and to be ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, which is the queſtion under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, but do not theſe things rather ſhew the contrary, and that they had but a name to be thus, but were dead and without Chriſt; and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> which was one of the ſeven
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119669:30"/>Churches, doth the Lord ſay there were any of that Church that were not in a ſaving ſtate, are any enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Church, let the Author read, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.7. to 13. and then let him tell us how he cometh to know that there were ſuch in that Church as were not true Saints, and the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed, I am ſure he that is holy and true in his meſſage to them, ſaith no ſuch thing, findes no ſuch fault with them as he doth with the reſt of the Churches, but truly whatſoever this Author ſaith, it would have been well if all the members of all thoſe Churches had been ſuch as have Chriſt to be the Lord their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and truly received Chriſt into their hearts to be their Lord and Chriſt, for then it would have been well with them for ever, though this Author makes ſuch a ſtate but the firſt image, and moſt unwarrantably calls ſuch the devils ſubjects, <hi>page</hi> 361.</p>
               <p>Page 151. [He ſaith, <hi>Thoſe that come into this firſt image, (who yet he ſaith are not in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtate) have by Chriſt renewed in them the ſame pure nature for kind, wherein man was at firſt created, and in that ſtate are fed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed up at Chriſts own Table, eating his fleſh, and drinking his blood, to the growing up into one living body with him.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatſoever this Author ſaith of the natural mans having the ſame pure nature for kind
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119669:30"/>that was in <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt, if we will believe the Scriptures, they will tell us the contrary, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>And God ſaw that the wickedneſſe of man was great in the earth, and that every ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of his heart was onely evil continually;</hi> where then was the pure nature for kinde that man was at firſt created in; and in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> its ſaid, that God looked down from heaven, and behold there was none righteous, no not one; and <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9. <hi>The heart is deceitful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, yea deſperately wicked, who can know it;</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaved;</hi> which plainly imports thus much, that though there may be a great deal of outward reformation in the natural man, yet the hearts of none are truly waſhed from wickedneſſe and purified, but they ſhall be ſaved; and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. the Apoſtle ſaith of the falſe teachers, (who yet no queſtion made a fair ſhew) that they had eyes full of adultery, or of the Whore, and could not ceaſe to ſin, where was the ſame pure nature in kinde that was in <hi>Adam,</hi> when they could not ceaſe to ſin; but the Author ſaith further, that theſe men are nouriſhed up at Chriſts own Table, eating his fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his blood; but he is ſufficiently miſtaken, for what is it to be nouriſhed up at Chriſts Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but to be nouriſhed up in faith, love, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and is the natural man thus nouriſhed up?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119669:31"/>what is this but to be nouriſhed up to eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life? and whereas he ſaith, they eat his fleſh, and drink his blood, I anſwer then they muſt needes be ſaved, if we will beleive Chriſts owne expreſſe words, <hi>John</hi> 6.54. who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternall <hi>life;</hi> for though this Author maketh nothing of eating Chriſts fleſh, and drinking his blood, and maketh it but his firſt Image, in which there is no ſalvation, yet ſaith Chriſt in the 55. <hi>verſe</hi> of that chap: <hi>My fleſh is meate indeed, and my blood is drink indeed, He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him;</hi> and leaſt we ſhould beleive ſuch doctrine as this Author bringeth, that this is but the firſt Image or Covenant of works, and falleth ſhort of ſalvation to eate Chriſts fleſh, and drink his blood, the Lord Jeſus maketh a ſolemne aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to evince it, he ſaith in 57. <hi>verſe,</hi> As the living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo he that eateth me, ſhall live by me; Thus notably hath Chriſt confuted this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors doctrine, and left it upon record for a witneſs againſt him, he ſaith further, that by thus eating of Chriſts fleſh, and drinking his blood, they grew up into one living body with him, and yet by his doctrine in no ſaving ſtate for all this, ſo that men may be living members of Chriſt, and yet never be ſaved, ſtrange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine indeed! ſhall any that are one living body
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119669:31"/>with Chriſt be damned? the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.23. that Chriſt is the Saviour of the body, and I think wee may believe him, but he quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.25.26. How men ſhall plead they have eaten and drunk in Chriſts preſence, and he hath taught in their ſtreetes, but what is this to the purpoſe? did all that ſat at table with Chriſt in the daies of his fleſh, and eat and drink with him, eat his fleſh, and drink his blood, and were all thoſe that heard him teach in their ſtreets made one liveing body with him; this would be as ſtrange an inference from this place, as thoſe that conclude 7. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments from the five loaves and 2. fiſhes, and alas theſe were ſo far from being one living bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with Chriſt, that the next <hi>verſe</hi> telleth us, that Chriſt ſhall ſay to them, I know not where you are, and ſo far from having pure nature of the ſame kind with <hi>Adam,</hi> that Chriſt ſhall ſay to them, Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity.</p>
               <p>What a ſlurre he caſts upon the Godly and Churches of Chriſt, <hi>Page</hi> 153. <hi>calling them the worldly church, the incorporated body of viſible Saints, called out and ſeparated from the world,</hi> a very cleaver contradicition, for if they be called out and ſeparated from the world, how are they a worldly church, yea, and he after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, they have a manifeſt ſelfe-diſtinguiſhing proreſſion, not onely from all heatheniſh wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119669:32"/>but from corrupt Chriſtian profeſſions and practiſes, but then will I aske this Author how then are they a worldly Church?</p>
               <p>Page 154. [<hi>He ſaith, that theſe are a true Church, and as</hi> Revel. 12.1. <hi>are cloathed with the Sun, yea, are the Nurſery or womb of all the true Spirituall ſeede.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But if they be the true Church of Chriſt, then they are in a ſaving ſtate, and then they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.24. Chriſt loveth them, and hath given himſelfe for them, <hi>v.</hi> 25. and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them to himſelfe a glorious Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, holy and without blemiſh, ſanctifies and cleanſes them, by the waſhing of the water through the word, <hi>v.</hi> 25.29. and ſurely all this amounts to eternall ſalvation, and to be cloathed with Chriſt, the Son of righteouſneſs, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. wrapt up in theſe beames of light and life, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth ſalvation fully, and I pray how can theſe be the nurſery and wombe of all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſeede, and yet not be the ſpirituall ſeede themſelves, he maketh theſe but fleſh in their higheſt attainements; and <hi>John</hi> 3.6. that which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh, and no better, he maketh them but the Law and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of workes, and doth he think the Law and its righteouſneſs, is the nurſery and wombe of all the ſpirituall ſeed, the Apoſtle will teach us another leſſon, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. where he asketh the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119669:32"/>
                  <hi>Galatians</hi> ſuch a queſtion, received ye the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by the hearing of the Law, or by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, was the Law or firſt Covenant the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery or wombe which brought forth the Spirit in you, ſurely no, but the hearing of faith, and ſo <hi>Gala.</hi> 4.23. he who was of the bond-woman was after the fleſh, but he that was of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was by promiſe, the bondwoman and all that are her children are in bondage. Now this Author counts this Church, and this ſtate that we are treating on, to be but the bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp; the Law, and yet ſaith, this is the nurſery and wombe of all the ſpirituall ſeed, but v. 30. <hi>What ſaith the Scripture, caſt out the bond-woman and her Son, for the Son of the bond-woman ſhall not be heire with the Son of the freewoman; but he ſaith</hi> v. 26. <hi>Jeruſalem that is above is free, which is the Mother of us all.</hi> The new Covenant of grace, that is the womb, the nurſery, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all, not the Law, the bond-woman, and telleth us plainly in the laſt verſe, that we are not the children of the bond-woman, but of the free: thus we ſee how this Author claſheth with the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Page 166. <hi>And in divers other places, he makes uſe of the</hi> 2 Cor. 5.16. <hi>to prove his doctrine, that Chriſt may be known, received into the heart as Lord and Chriſt, and yet no ſaving ſtate, the words are theſe, wherefore henceforth know we no man after the fleſh, yea, though we have knowne Chriſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119669:33"/>after the fleſh, yet henceforth know wee him no more.</hi>]</p>
               <p>What is the meaning of this Scripture, we may underſtand it thus, wherefore henceforth know wee not man after the fleſh, that is to ſay, <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> that becauſe a man is a <hi>Jew,</hi> that therefore he muſt pe accounted one of Gods people, or becauſe he is a Gentile, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt be a loſt creature without hope, &amp; without God in the world, yea, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, that is, have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him onely as a Jew; and of the ſeed of <hi>David,</hi> according to the fleſh, but we henceforth look upon him on more <hi>Barely</hi> under ſuch a conſideration, but as he that is the onely begotten Son of God, full of grace and truth, wee know him as he that was ſent into the world to ſave ſinners, and was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our offences, and roſe againe for our juſtification, as the verſe before ſaith, that he dyed for us, and roſe againe, or take it thus, though we, that is, ſome of us, the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt, have converſed with Chriſt in the fleſh when he dwelt amongſt us, and had too humane and natural affection to his bodily preſence, yet we knowing, as <hi>John</hi> 6.36. that it is the ſpirit that quickens, the fleſh profiteth nothing; that the bodily Preſence of Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing without the preſence of his grace,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119669:33"/>righteouſneſſe, and ſpirit in our hearts; hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth we know him no more after that manner, but our love and affections are ſet upon Chriſt, as he that hath offered up himſelfe in the eternall ſpirit, to obtain an eternal redemption for us, and has aſcended to his Father, and to our father, to his God, and to our God, where he ever liveth to make interceſſion for us, and therefore I doe not ſee, how this place will make in the leaſt for the Authors doctrine, but he maketh to know Chriſt after the fleſh, to be the receiving of Chriſt into the heart, as Lord and Chriſt, and being juſtified by his blood, and ſanctified by his ſpirit, according to the firſt image, as he calls it, I hope ſuch knowledg of Chriſt ſhould be retained, not thrown up, though he calls it but the firſt image.</p>
               <p>Page 170. [He ſaith, <hi>God is pleaſed through the blood of Chriſt to declare himſelf reconciled to the whole Race of mankind, beholding them in the ſeed of the woman, the ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>and to prove this, quotes</hi> 2 Cor. 5. Jer. 31. <hi>compared with</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel 18. <hi>where he ſaith, Chriſt challenges all ſouls to be his.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But the Author ſhould have quoted the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of thoſe chapters that he thought would prove this, and ſhould have ſhewn how he would have argued from them, and then I would have taken the pains to have anſwered him, though there is no need at all, ſeeing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119669:34"/>
                  <hi>Perkins, Twiſſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kendall,</hi> and others, have ſo fully canvaſſed that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of generall redemption, to whom the Church of God owe much for their labours and travels in that point; but whereas he ſaith, that in that <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. its ſaid, <hi>all ſoules are mine,</hi> what if it be ſpoken of God as Creator, and not of Chriſt as Redeemer, nay, plainly enough it appears ſo to be meant, if we view the place, and let the Reader well conſider <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>If we were reconciled by Chriſts blood, how much more ſhall we be ſaved by his life, by him reigning in heaven, and ſit down at the right hand of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in the ſame page he ſaith, <hi>That this is ſo evident, that the creature it ſelf,</hi> Rom. 8.19.20. <hi>entrneſtly groans and labours, exſpecting a reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by this price of redemption paid by Chriſt.</hi>]</p>
               <p>There is no queſtion but the creature, <hi>ſuo modo,</hi> according to its own manner and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, both waits for a reſtoration, and for the manifeſtation of the ſons of God, but doth this make the point of univerſal redemption e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident? ſurely no, for I hope that the Author will not ſay, that Chriſt died for their irrationall creatures, then indeed we might do as he did, that went and preached to the Wolfes and wild beaſts; truly this which he ſaith maketh it ſo evident to me, comes not within many miles of a clear proof, or any at all of univerſall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119669:34"/>
               <p>Page 172. <hi>He ſaith, of thoſe in this firſt image, that God doth not impute ſins paſt to them, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reneweth pardon to them for ſins preſent, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing his forbearance for the ſake of his own Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as pacified and attoned by Chriſts Sacrifice, and for this he quotes</hi> Pſal. 78.38.</p>
               <p>But I pray what ſins doth the Author ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſins paſt, that God doth not impute, what all ſins before their coming into this i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, all their unbelief, pride, hatred of God, and all their ſins whatſoever, before they came to have this union with Chriſt, he calls union with Chriſt in the fleſh, and doth he think that the gifts and calling of God are not without repentance? doth God juſtifie, and unjuſtifie again? pardon, and then fall upon the ſinner, croſſe the book, and then make him pay the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing, no, with him is no variableneſs, nor ſhadow of changeing, once pardon, and ever pardon, once our God in Chriſt, and ever ſo; its one thing for God to exerciſe forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to men, and another thing to pardon their ſins, its one thing to forbear the debt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing to forgive it, and cancel the bond, this forbearance is no payment, nor forgiveneſs of the debt, though God doth not preſently ſue the bond, and vengeance be not executed ſpeedily, yet this doth not argue that he hath forgiven the debt: But let us ſee whether the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119669:35"/>Scripture he quots, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.38. prove what he ſaith, the words run thus, <hi>but he being full of compaſſion for gave their iniquity and deſtroyed them not, yea, many a time turned he his anger away, and did not ſtir up all his wrath:</hi> But with forgiveneſs was this, but that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of that people God was propitious to them, as the word is often rendred, and did not ſtir up all his wrath, and the elect a mong them their ſins were Covered for ever by the robe of Chriſts righteouſneſs; let us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Scripture with Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.2. with this place, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe tranſgreſſions are forgiven, whoſe ſin is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth not iniquity;</hi> where the Holy Ghoſt plainly maketh it a ſtate of bleſſedneſſe and ſalvation to have our iniquities forgiven, and our ſins covered, that ſo the Analogy of faith and harmony, that one Scripture hath with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, teacheth us how to underſtand that Scripture, to wit, that it was the elect among the Jewes whoſe iniquities were truly forgiven, the reſt were forgiven in the ſenſe there decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is to ſay, ſo as they were not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed, neither did God ſtir up all his wrath, but when ever he puniſhed that people yet, he left a ſeed, he ſpared ſome, he did not deal with them as with <hi>Sodome,</hi> nor make them
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119669:35"/>like to <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> but why doth the Author think that all the Jewes were in that ſtate, which he calls the firſt image, its ſaid, ver. 36.37. <hi>That they flattered God with their mouths, and lyed to him with their tongues, and their heart was not right with him, how were they then ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by a real and actual change of the heart, which the Author makes the first image,</hi> yea, ver. 10. of that Pſalm, its ſaid, they refuſed to walk in Gods Law, how then were they in this ſtate that the Author talks on? <hi>they would have their high places, and graven images, ver.</hi> 58. <hi>ſurely thoſe were none of the Authors Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 173. He ſaith, <hi>The Gyants ſpoken of,</hi> Gen. 6. <hi>were in the firſt image.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have ſeen before what he maketh the firſt image to be, to wit, to receive Chriſt into the heart as Lord and Chriſt in his firſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and to eat his fleſh, and drink his blood, and doth any body think theſe Gyants did ſo? they were called Gyants, becauſe of their great ſtatute, and Lion-like ſtrength and diſpoſition not I wis for any holineſſe they had more then other men, for holineſſe and grace they might ſhake hands with their brother <hi>Goliah,</hi> whom <hi>David</hi> ſlew, they were men of renown for the greatneſſe and ſtrength of their bodies, not for the goodneſſe and holineſſe of their hearts;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119669:36"/>truly thoſe Gyants are much beholden to this Author for the good opinion he hath of them, for other men think they were wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men, that lived without God in the world, and I would fain have him ſhew us one expreſſion in all that 6. of <hi>Gen.</hi> that ſheweth them to be in ſuch a ſtate as he calls the firſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
               <p>Page 185. and 186. <hi>That thoſe that are in the firſt image, are taken out of that ſtock the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>and are tranſplanted into the good Olive tree (the man Chriſt Jeſus) and made to partake of the fatneſſe thereof,</hi> Rom. 11. <hi>becoming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wholly a right ſeed,</hi> Jer. 2.21. <hi>a holy and righteous ſeed in the principles and operations of their mind, anſwerable to the holy and righteous fleſh of Chriſt, and are taught to ſee the need of coming to God, and being accepted with him in the ſacrifice or death of Chriſt, who as conſidered as coming in the fleſh, is given to them for a new head and root, yet he ſaith, they become exalters of this their legall righteouſneſſe againſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the knowledge of the Croſſe of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. hath another meaning, yet let us take it in his ſenſe, and ſee what it will hold forth in this matter, to be tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Chriſt, and to partake of the fatneſſe of that good Olive tree, ſurely this is a ſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate, a man cannot be taken out of the old
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119669:36"/>
                  <hi>Adam,</hi> and be truly tranſplanted into Chriſt, but he muſt be grafted upon the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and planted into the likeneſſe of his death, ſpoken of <hi>Romans</hi> 6. and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of Chriſts fatneſſe, is to receive of his fulneſs, and grace for grace, to derive, quickning, ſtrengthening, ſanctifying, comforting, and all grace from Chriſt a bleſſed ſtate, and for holineſſe he ſaith, they are anſwerable to the holy and righteous fleſh of Chriſt, good ſtill, and I would fain ſee ſuch a man that is thus, &amp; is not in a ſaving ſtate, I am ſure the Gyants he talked on before, were far enough from this ſtate, and I would we could all finde ſuch principles and operations of minde in us, that the ſame minde were in us that was in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.5. That we had the ſame minde for humility, the ſame minde for patience, the ſame minde for ſubmiſſion to the Fathers will, the ſame minde for ſelf-deniall, the ſame minde for contentment in all eſtates, the ſame minde for publique Spiritedneſs, the ſame minde for tender love and affections to the Saintes, the ſame minde for pitty and compaſſion to mens ſoules, But truly inſtead of theſe notions, that the naturall man may have principles and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of minde anſwerable to the holy and righteous fleſh of Chriſt, we ſhould rather exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our own conformity unto him, and mourn
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119669:37"/>for our ſhort coming in theſe things, who ſhould have the ſame minde in us, that alſo was in Chriſt Jeſus. And he thinketh theſe in the firſt image are taught too, he ſaith, to ſee their neede of being accepted in the beloved, in the ſacrifice or death of Chriſt; good ſtill, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they that are thus taught of God to ſee their owne righteouſneſs, a covering too ſcant for them, and look truly to be accepted in Chriſt, are built upon the Rock that the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt; but he ſaith, for all this they became exalters of this their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall righteouſneſs, againſt the excellency of the knowledge of the croſſe of Chriſt, what doth he meane by their legall righteouſneſs, which they exalt? no other but the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, who he ſuppoſeth to be their legall righteouſneſs, who are in the firſt image, and their Evangelicall righteouſneſs, who are in his ſecond image, for he maketh it all one to have this kind of righteouſneſs either inherent in us, or by Chriſt imputed to us, and maketh the truſting to it, whether as inherent in us, or as inherent in Chriſt, and made ours by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be a truſting in our owne righteouſneſs, and mans righteouſneſs, for that kind of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in Chriſt, he maketh but mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and but fleſh, a dangerous miſtake, but the Scripture diſtinguiſheth between them in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119669:37"/>many places, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.4. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. verſe, and ſo on, and ſo he diſtinguiſheth that ſort of righteouſneſſe which was in Chriſt as he fulfilled the Law, and bear the curſe of it for us to be but mans righteouſneſſe, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to thoſe that ſhall never be ſaved, and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as he was taken up into the higher image, he calls the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, not conſidering the reaſon why the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is called Gods righteouſneſſe in many places of Scripture, as 1. becauſe it is the righteouſneſſe of him that was both God and man, and therefore his blood is called <hi>Acts</hi> 20. the blood of God, not that the divine nature could die, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that ſhed his blood upon the Croſſe, was both God and man. Again, ſecondly, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is called the righteouſneſſe of God, becauſe it is the righteouſneſs God accepts for juſtification, and hath appointed for the ſalvation and juſtification of his people, and the onely righteouſneſs that he imputeth to us, when he juſtifieth us, and thus it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. that they being ignorant of Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and going about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſſe, have not ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the righteouſneſſe of God, that is to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119669:38"/>ſay, they not knowing that Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs was the only righteouſneſs that God would accept for the juſtification of a ſinner, they went about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſſe, they thought their own obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and righteouſneſſe would doe it, and ſo never ſaw the ſhortneſs of their owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to bring them unto life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never ſubmited to the righteouſneſs of God, never came to Chriſt that they might have life. Thirdly, Chriſts righteouſneſs may be called Gods righteouſneſs, becauſe Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed to us, declares Gods righteouſneſſe in juſtifying of us, that he is juſt in it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29.</p>
               <p>Page 188. <hi>He ſaith, that the Apoſtles meaning</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>when he ſaith the Law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth, is that the Law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth unto Chriſt as his bridegroom &amp; husband, under the firſt covenant, &amp; are as it were his married wife,</hi> Iſaiah 54.1. <hi>bearing Children, or becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fruitfull unto Chriſt in that ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I wis his meaning is, that the law hath dominion over a man, that is, hath power to curſe us, and condemn us, ſo long as we live under it as a Covenant of workes; for ſo here the Apoſtle is ſhewing the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a man that is united to Chriſt, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119669:38"/>one that is not united to Chriſt, not the difference betweene a man that is united to Chriſt in the fleſh, and a man that is united to Chriſt in the higher image, as this Author ſuppoſes, and how plainly doth this Author contradict himſelfe herein, for page 118. he telleth us, that thoſe that are married to Chriſt, and receive him according to the firſt covenant, that they have the benefit of Chriſts legall righteouſneſſe, by which he ſatisfied the <hi>Law, ſo that he ſaith, the law hath nothing to ſay againſt ſuch, but here he ſaith the Law hath dominion over ſuch,</hi> that is, hath power to curſe them and condemne them, if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth not plainly contradict himſelfe in theſe two places, let the reader judge; and he goes on here to tel us, that in this ſtate men are married to Chriſt, &amp; bear Children, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fruitfull unto him, truly then our iſſue are not baſtards, when we are married to Chriſt, beare children, and are fruitfull to him, ſurely Chriſt will for ever owne ſuch to be his ſpouſes, and their Iſſue to be his, but what <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. will prove for him, I know not, neither is he pleaſed to tell us how he will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from it, but I am ſure it will make againſt him, for thoſe that are there ſaid, now to beare and bring forth fruit, are ſaid in the 5.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119669:39"/>verſe, to have their Maker to be their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and ver. 8. God ſaith with everlaſting kindneſſe he will have mercy on them, which ſurely is a ſaving ſtate.</p>
               <p>Page 189. <hi>He ſaith the fleſhly ſeed of Iſrael were implanted into Chriſt, ſo that by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and not by their owne, they were made righteous, and in him, as in the firſt fruits, the whole lumpe was rendred holy.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The elect among the children of Iſrael were ſo, but we ſhall ſtay long enough before the Author can prove that all the fleſhly ſeed of Iſraell were implanted into Chriſt, and made righteous by his righteouſneſs, if they had, they had ſurely been in a ſaving ſtate, will the Author never leave undervaluing the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and ſaying that a man may be made righteous, not in his owne righteouſneſs, but in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate, the worſt I wiſh the Author is, that he may be righteous in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt (which he hath lifted up his hand ſo high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in his booke) that ſo he may finde mercy in that day, when he muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his booke, and of all things he hath done in the body, if the righteouſneſs of Chriſt will not ſtand us in ſtead, we periſh for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119669:39"/>ever; He is miſtaken in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. for by the firſt fruits there ſpoken of is not meant Chriſt, but <hi>Abraham</hi> with whom God made ſuch a gracious Govenant, according to which the Jewes ſhall at laſt finde favour in Gods eyes, who are beloved for that Fathers ſake, and therefore the Scripture often tells us, that when the Jews provoked God, he remember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Govenant that he made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and did not forget the Covenant of their Fathers which he ſware unto them.</p>
               <p>Page 190. <hi>He applies,</hi> 2 <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>verſes, to men in his firſt image, that they are made partakers of all that is there ſpoken.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we will try that, the eleventh verſe it is thus, <hi>in whom alſo ye are circumciſed with your circumciſion, made without hands, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of Chriſt.</hi> I do not a little mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell that he ſhould apply this to men in the firſt image, wherein there is no ſalvation, for who doth the Apoſtle ſpeak theſe of, but of ſuch as in the chapter before he calls Saints, faithful, verſe 2. ſaith, that they had faith in the Lord Jeſus, and love to all the Saints, telleth them, there was hope laid up for them in heaven, verſe 5. and ſecond chap.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119669:40"/>10. tells them, they were compleat in Chriſt, and were not ſuch as theſe in a ſaving ſtate, to have true faith in the Lord Jeſus, and be compleat in him, is not this a ſaving ſtate? And now the Apoſtle goeth on further to ſhew what theſe believers had received from Chriſt, how your hearts were circumciſed by the circumciſion that Chriſt is the worker of, which is no other but the true regeneration of the ſpirit, and verſe 13. ſaith, how they were quickned together with Chriſt, and all their treſpaſſes forgiven them, if to be thus, be not a ſaving ſtate, I know not what is, and let this Author have a care of miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Scripture in this manner, wreſting the Scriptures to make out his notions of his images, and thus calling light darkneſſe, calling true regeneration, and the faith of Gods elect, but common grace.</p>
               <p>Page 191. He ſaith, <hi>thoſe that are in the first image, have writ out in the fleſhly table of their hearts, a conformity to that image of God that ſhines forth in the fleſh of Chriſt, and this is their ſanctification; and there, and page</hi> 192. <hi>he ſaith too, that Chriſt himſelfe is made their head and covering, as to their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, they are made righteous, not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but in another, even through the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119669:40"/>of the man Chriſt Jeſus, as their Head, in whoſe natural righteouſneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection they ſtand blameleſſe before God.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed for juſtification, and Chriſts righteouſneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted for our ſanctification, and yet the Author would make us believe all this is not a ſaving ſtate, but I wis the writing of Gods Laws in our hearts, is a peculiar benefit of the new Covenant of grace, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. but he maketh it to be given as a benefit by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of the old Covenant again by Chriſt, and ô how diſhonorable is this to Chriſt the Lord of life, that men may have him for their head and covering, for their juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate; but what ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. Thoſe whom the Lord juſtifieth, them he alſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies, then which what can be plainer to prove, that ſuch as are juſtified by Chriſt, are in a ſaving ſtate, for the text tells us, ſuch ſhall be glorified, let this Author ſay what he will to the contrary, that this is but the firſt image, and Chriſt in the fleſh, the ſure word of the Goſpel, tells us, that thoſe whom the Lord juſtifies, ſhall certainly be glorified, brought to heaven, inherit eternal life; and whereas he ſaith, Chriſt is made their cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119669:41"/>for juſtification, then I ſay they muſt needs be in a ſure and ſaving ſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe iniquities are pardoned, and whoſe ſinnes are covered by the robes of Chriſts righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſuch can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come into condemnation, God ſeeth no iniquity in ſuch with a judicial eye, to take vengeance and damn them for it, for Chriſt covereth their ſins in that reſpect, that in that ſenſe God ſeeth no iniquity in <hi>Jacob,</hi> nor no tranſgreſſion in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but only ſeeth the ſins of ſuch with the eye of a Father, (which is well for them) to reclaim them, better them, and heal their backſlidings, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.18. We ſee the Author makes no bones of counting Chriſts righteouſneſſe invalid for juſtification, and yet ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting himſelf, ſaith, that this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſts, makes us to ſtand blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe before God, but then are not ſuch in a ſaving ſtate, if we be blameleſſe by Chriſt before God, then I may ask this Author, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.34. who ſhall lay any thing to their charge? who ſhall condemne them, ſeeing God Juſtifies them, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor confeſſes they ſtand blameleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119669:41"/>
               <p>Page 193. <hi>He ſaith, theſe are repreſented in</hi> Pauls <hi>owne perſon,</hi> Rom 7. <hi>as having that workmanſhip ſet up in their hearts and mindes, which ſtands in an exact conformity to the Law or image of Chriſts natural righteouſneſs; but in the next page, he ſaith, they find by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence no good thing dwelling in their fleſh, that is, abiding, and of a continual reſidence with them, being in ſuch a wavering condition,</hi> that whileſt with their minde they ſerve the Law of God, they are ready with their fleſh to ſerve the Law of ſin, and the good they would doe, that they doe not, and the evill which they would not doe, that they doe.</p>
               <p>But ſtay, firſt the Author is miſtaken in this, that he thinketh the true ſaints that ſhall inherit eternall life are not repreſented by <hi>Pauls</hi> own perſon, that which is there ſaid in that 7. of <hi>Rom.</hi> was true of <hi>Paul,</hi> and then ſurely as true of other ſaints; and this Author goeth about here to make <hi>Paul</hi> but in the firſt image, for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith all that of himſelf, and the Author thinketh this was but the firſt image, and calls this a being under the Law; alas he that mindes the 9.10.11. verſes of that Chap. will ſee that <hi>Paul,</hi> and the perſons repreſented in him, were of from the Law for life, for he ſaith,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119669:42"/>the Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew him, he found that to be but death, well, but why muſt this be but a man in the firſt image, and out of a ſaving ſtate? why the Author ſaith, that theſe have no good thing dwelling in their fleſh, that is, faith he, abiding and of a continuall reſidence with them; but hold a little, that is not the meaning of it, for in us, that is, in our fleſh, is nothing ſpiritually good, not only that there is nothing that doth abide and continue, but there is nothing at all good in us by nature, in me, that is in my fleſh, that is, as I am na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and as conſidered without the grace and ſpirit of God, ſo I have no good thing dwelling in me, and ſo it is with every ſaint of God, that they may all ſay as he ſaid, <hi>Horreo quicquid de meo eſt,</hi> I abhominate what is of my ſelf, or with <hi>Paul, in me, that is in my fleſh, dwells no good thing;</hi> I have no good in me, no good thoughts, deſires, inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but as God worketh in me to will, and to doe of his owne good pleaſure; but I pray let the Author ſhew us any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but that a man in his higher image may not have cauſe to ſay and confeſſe as much, that in them, that is, in their fleſh, dwells no good thing; in a word, there doth not onely no good thing abide and continue
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119669:42"/>in our hearts by nature, but it was never there to be found, but we are tranſgreſſors from the wombe.</p>
               <p>Well, he ſaith further, as v. 25. <hi>that whileſt with their minde they ſerve the law of God, they are ready with their fleſh to ſerve the law of ſin;</hi> and I pray who is not ſo? <hi>Paul</hi> there ſaith it was ſo with him, and we are content to acknowledge it is ſo with us, though the Author for it ſay we are but in the firſt Image, we confeſſe we are fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the fleſh in us rebelleth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and while we with our minds and hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſerve the law of God, and doe his will, the fleſh in us draweth another way, this enemy in our owne boſomes, the fleſh and law of our members is often too hard for us, and brings us into captivity, this is our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, our gall, and wormwood in this world, and makes us cry out often with <hi>Paul,</hi> ver. 24. <hi>O wretched man that we are,</hi> and with <hi>Iſaiah, we are uncleane, we are uncleane;</hi> and yet for all this, we know that the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin, and the ſpirit of Chriſt will ſanctifie us wholly, and caſt all our ſinnes into the depths of the Sea, and the time will come when we ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119669:43"/>ſin no more, and all things in us ſhall be made ſubject to Chriſt, though we ſee not yet all things made ſubject unto Chriſt, yet having faith in Chriſt, the work is doing, and we ſhall be purified one day, even as he is pure, and our ſanctification ſhall be as compleat and perfect hereafter, as our juſtification is here; the remainders of corruption are left in the ſaints in this world, to keep them low and vile in their own eyes, to make them prize and value the blood of Chriſt, which cleanſeth them from all ſin, to keep them from going about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſſe, to make them deſire to be diſſolved to be with Chriſt, to imbitter the world to them, to let them ſee their owne weakeneſſe and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſſe, and in judgment to the world, that they are oftentimes hardened and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced againſt the wayes of God, by the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſpots of Gods children, but they are ſaints for all this remainder of corruption, and I doe believe a man in the Authors ſecond Image, may complaine of this as well as <hi>Paul</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>But the Author goes on, and ſaith, as v. 19. <hi>that theſe in the firſt Image, the good which they would doe, that they doe not, and the evill
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119669:43"/>which they would not doe, that they do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſurely is true of all Saints in this world, they do not pray, hear, meditate, live unto God as they deſire, and by the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of corruption are often hindered from doing the good which they would, and ſurely were it not that it is ſo at preſent with the beſt ſaints, that they cannot doe the good which they would, they would be more holy, and heavenly, and ſpiritual, and thankfull, and ſincere, and active for God then they are, if they could do the things which they would, and again, were it not that the ſaints are ſo, that the evill which they would not, that they doe, there would not be that pride, deadneſs, earthlineſs in the ſaints that there is, for they pray againſt their corruptions with ſtrong crying and teares, and had rather be freed from them, then from any croſſes and afflictions whatſoever; thus we have examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whither <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſeventh of the <hi>Romans</hi> doth repreſent in his owne perſon a man that is in the Authors firſt image, and nor in a ſaving ſtate; we ſee the contrary, that <hi>Paul</hi> here doth perſonate the true ſaints, and what is there ſaid, is true of all ſaints this ſide glory.</p>
               <p>Page 207. <hi>He ſaith, theſe are but after ſuch
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119669:44"/>a manner Chriſts houſe, as is intimated,</hi> Heb. 3.6. <hi>whoſe houſe are we, if we hold faſt the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and the rejoycing of the hope firme un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this place proveth not that any are the houſe, and of the family of Chriſt, that yet do periſh and miſcarry for ever, but quite contrary, that none are his houſe, and of his family, but thoſe that do hold faſt the faith, and endure to the end; that this perſeverance is an evidence of true grace, as Chriſt ſaid, if you continue to the end, then are ye my <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples indeed,</hi> elſe you are my diſciples but in ſhew, ſo if you hold faſt the confidence and faith, which you profeſſe to have in the Lord Jeſus, then you are Chriſts houſe indeed, elſe you have but onely a name, to live a name, to be Chriſts houſe &amp; members, and this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor muſt needs, according to the tenour of his judgement, make the confidence here ſpoken of to be but ſuch as a man hath in the firſt image, and he maketh the throwing it up, and not the keeping of it, to be the way to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Page 208. He ſaith, <hi>This ſtate is called in Scripture the firſt faith which may be departed from; and prove a faith that failes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:119669:44"/>
               <p>I ſuppoſe the place of Scripture the Author meanes, is 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.12. the Apoſtle is there ſpeaking of widdowes, for the ſervice of the Church, to viſit the ſicke, and the like, and wiſheth them not to chuſe young women to that office, for he ſaith when they have waxed wanton againſt Chriſt, they will mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, having damnation, becauſe they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken their firſt faith; there is no neceſſity that we ſhould underſtand here by damnation, eternall damnation, but that they are to be faulted and condemned for going from their faith and promiſe to continue ſingle for the ſervice of the Church; if we will underſtand it of faith in Chriſt, then thoſe that leave it did but ſeem to have it, as in theſe parables, one Evangeliſt ſaith, from him ſhall be taken that which he hath, the other Evangeliſt explaines it thus, that which he ſeemeth to have, ſo many men leave the faith, ſincerity, &amp; holyneſs, which they once ſeemed to have, but however this place be underſtood, it will make nothing for this Auther, for they are ſaid to have damnation, becauſe they left their firſt faith, now if this firſt faith were the Authors firſt image, yet he maketh not the leaving of this firſt image, but the keeping it, and ſiting downe in it, to be mens damnation.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119669:45"/>
               <p>Page 209. <hi>He makes Chriſts ſecond appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſpoken of,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14. <hi>to be the higher image, that the firſt image is to be kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot unto.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But that appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, is his 2. coming, when he ſhall come with 10000. of his ſaints to execute judgment upon all that are ungodly, and take to him his great power and raign; but its the Authors way to make ſcripture bow downe to his image, and ſo in the ſame page he makes the Angells calling to <hi>Jacob</hi> to let him go, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26. that Angell, to ſignifie the firſt Image, which calls to be let goe, becauſe of the day breake of Chriſts ſecond coming, the higher Image; he that ſhall thus expound Scripture may even ſay what he will, and ſurely if the Author doth not quote theſe, and moſt of the Scriptures he quotes, meerly for illuſtration, and to uſe Scripture phraſe, and not at all to prove what he is about, he will be deeply guilty of that which the Apoſtles call wreſting of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>Page 210. He ſaith, <hi>theſe are ſaid</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.12. <hi>to have faith accompanied with a good conſcience, but ſuch as may be loſt and ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt. The words are theſe, holding faith and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119669:45"/>a good conſcience, which ſome having put away concerning faith, have made ſhipwrack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is the faith that <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy</hi> hold faſt here, not ſo much the grace of faith in his owne heart, but it is the doctrine of faith, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf elſewhere, I have fought a good fight, I have kept the faith, and ſo he would have <hi>Timothy</hi> againſt all oppoſers, and this doctrine of faith, he had ſaid downe in ver. 15. which was this, that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners; now <hi>Hymenus</hi> and <hi>Phyletus,</hi> and ſuch as had onely received a notionall knowledge of this doctrine, had not received this truth in the love and power of it, not having a good conſcience, and hearts brought to the obedience of Chriſt, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this faith they made ſhipwrack, God gave them up to ſtrong deluſions to believe a lie, they fell into errors concerning the faith and waies of Chriſt, and ſaid the reſurrection was paſt already, and ſo overthrew the faith of ſome that were perſwaded of the contrary before, ſo that this place proveth not, that men may have true faith in Chriſt and loſe it; the notionall and hiſtoricall faith and beliefe of the Goſpel may be loſt, and men may ſin away ſuch inlightnings and convictions of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119669:46"/>the ſpirit, but ſuch faith as truly receives Chriſt into the heart, and unites us unto him in the greateſt ſtormes, will not be ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt, and that man having this faith and hope in Chriſt, hath an Anchor for his ſoule both ſure and ſtedfaſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. ult. this faith ſwims in the ſea of Chriſts blood, in the Ocean of free grace, where it cannot ſuffer ſhipwrack.</p>
               <p>Page. 221. <hi>&amp;</hi> 222. <hi>He ſaith concerning Abrahams calling, that his firſt remove was out of the ſtate of degenerate nature, and his heatheniſh life, into circumciſion or experience of that commumon with God which is by the firſt Covenant, which he made uſe of but as an Iun in his paſſage to the higher ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Author had conſulted with the fourth <hi>Rom.</hi> he would have bloted out this paſſage, for in that Chap. the Apoſtle have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoken of juſtification, Gods imputing righteouſneſs without workes, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering their ſins no more, he telleth us in the 9.10.11.12. verſes, that before ever <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> received the ſigne of circumciſion, he was thus juſtified, and therefore had true ſaving faith, <hi>He received circumciſion, a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l of the righteouſneſs of faith which he had, being yet uncircumciſed, that he might be the father of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119669:46"/>all them that believe, though they be not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, that righteouſneſs might be imputed to them alſo;</hi> and the Author is miſtaken to think that circumciſion was a ſeale of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of workes, for it was a ſeale of the righteouſneſs of the new covenant, which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> had believed in before.</p>
               <p>Page 318. <hi>He ſaith, theſe under the firſt image (wherein yet there is not eternall life) are planted into Chriſt, as branches in the vine, and good olive tree, and ſo rendred righteous in the righteouſneſs of their head and root.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That place, <hi>John</hi> 15.1. Every branch in me that beareth not fruit is taken away, the learned very well, and according to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall read thus, <hi>Every branch that beareth not fruit in me is taken away,</hi> and ſo the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that though men beare never ſo much fruit by their husband the law, yet all theſe children are but baſtards, unleſſe they be married to Chriſt the true husband, and though ſuch may go for true ſaints, yet they are not, and doth not at all hold forth that any man may be truly in Chriſt, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate, which will be more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent if we compare this place with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>That there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119669:47"/>to them that are truly <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> &amp; planted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to ſuch there is no condemnation, but they are paſſed from death to life, and this Author confeſſes, that theſe men are rendred righteous in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, their head and root, and if ſo, what hinders their eternall ſalvation? will not Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs juſtifie them and ſave them for ever? we are content to leave it upon that iſſue, and venture our ſoules upon that ſcore, that if our being rendred righteous in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt our head and root, will not bring us to Heaven, we are willing to miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ever, but we know aſſuredly that his righteouſneſſe will juſtifie us for ever, and ſave us to the utmoſt, that come to God by him.</p>
               <p>In that Page 318. <hi>He ſaith, theſe go about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſs, not ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the righteouſneſs of God.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But hath not the Author often ſaid, that theſe men in the firſt image ſeek acceptance with God onely by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and in this ſame page ſaith, they are rendred righteous in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt their head, and if ſo, how do they go about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſneſs? but the myſtery lieth in the Authors under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119669:47"/>of the righteouſneſs of God, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing betweene the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and the righteouſneſs of God; but its the righteouſneſs of Chriſt that the Scripture calls the righteouſneſs of God, and we have ſhewed before why the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is called the righteouſneſs of God, not as if the righteouſneſs of Chriſt by which we are juſtified, was the eternall righteouſneſs of the Godhead, as <hi>Oſiander</hi> dreamed, which is not communicable unto us; but whatſoever the Author ſaith here of men in the firſt image, that they will not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God, yet page 118. he ſaith, they are made the righteouſneſs of God in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Page 320. <hi>He ſaith, theſe are begotten againe into Gods own likneſs, wherein man was created at firſt, and have the viſible characters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhining forth in it, not written with inke, and on tables of ſtone, but with the ſpirit of the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and on the fleſhly tables of the heart, ſhewing it ſelfe a right change, and a reall heart work, above and beyond all that is accounted ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and morality, and above all notion and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality, that is but head work and fancy, and the tempter perſwades them to reſt here, and praiſe and bleſſe Gods word; and makes them ſay
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119669:48"/>its good for us to be here, eſpecially if we be upon the Mount, and brought hither by Chriſt himſelf.</hi>]</p>
               <p>It being ſuppoſed what the Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, that theſe look for acceptance with God onely in the beloved, this is a bleſſed ſtate, and all they that are brought into it are taught of God, and not by the devill, as the Author imagines, to bleſſe Gods word, and be thankfull for this rich grace, and ſay its good for us to be here, whither ſhould we go, we are with him that hath alone the words of eternal life; we are with him that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies us, ſanctifies us, ſtays us with flaggons, comforts us with apples, quickens us, influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences us with his ſpirit, kiſſes us with the kiſſes of his mouth, whoſe love is better then wine, guides us by his counſell, and afterwards brings us to his glory, ſurely we may bleſſe the word of the Lord, and magnifie his grace, and ſay its good to be here, and bleſſe the Lord that he brought us to this bleſſed ſtate, and for ſanctification, who are partakers of it, as the Author here deſcribes it, but the true believers? its they onely that put on the new man, which after the image of God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſs, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3.3. rejoyced in ſuch, as the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119669:48"/>Epiſtle of Chriſt, whoſe hearts were ſo written on by the ſpirit of the living God; and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.10. its made a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall bleſſing of the new Covenant of grace, I will put my lawes into their minde, and write them in their hearts, ſuch have God to be their God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for ever, and they his people for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and though the heart of a naturall man may in ſome ſort be ſwept and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, yet not thus written on by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, as the Author ſaith.</p>
               <p>Page 325. He ſaith, <hi>That theſe in the firſt image have their conſciences purged from dead works by the blood of Chriſt, and ſo fitted againe for the ſervice of the living God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where doth the Scripture ſay thus, its the Saints onely that have their hearts purified by faith, the natural mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſo far from being purged from dead works, that all his works, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he or others think of them, yet in Gods eſteem they are dead works, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they come from him that is dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, void of the life and ſpirit of Chriſt, none of the living in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119669:49"/>and though he may have a name to live, yet he is dead, and his works dead works; and whereas he ſaith a man in the firſt image is fitted again for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the living God, then he muſt be a true believer, no man is fitted for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the living God, without he be a true believer, for without faith its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God; he muſt alſo be a ſpirituall worſhipper, for God is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and will be worſhipt in ſpirit and truth.</p>
               <p>Page 329. <hi>He ſaith further of theſe in the firſt image, that they feed myſtically upon Chriſts fleſh, and drink his blood, ſo as that they are nouriſhed up in a way of righteouſneſſe, like unto that of thoſe young men,</hi> 1 John 2.14. <hi>who were ſtrong through the word of God thus dwelling and abiding in them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had overcome the wicked one, as to all fleſhly impurity and filthineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the naturall man feeds myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally upon Chriſts fleſh and blood, we have diſproved before, and for thoſe in <hi>John,</hi> ſurely they were in a ſaving ſtate, they were ſtrong, ſurely not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119669:49"/>but in the Lord, and the power of his might, the word of God abided and dwelt in them, if we take it for Chriſt, they had him abiding in them, and ſurely they that abide in Chriſt, and have Chriſt abiding in them, are true Saints; if we take it as meant of the Goſpel, none have that word of Chriſt dwelling richly in them but Saints, and they have overcome the wicked one, conquered him through him that loved them, this is peculiar to the true Saints, and where the devill is truely overcome, its not onely as to the filthineſs of the fleſh, but of the ſpirit alſo, if the divell raigne in the heart, he is not yet overcome.</p>
               <p>Page 329. <hi>He ſaith, theſe men in the firſt image, and Chriſt, are ſo knit together in this ſort of marriage union, that Chriſt and they make but one fleſh, one bread, and one body, ſo as all the glory, beauty, comelineſſe, and perfection which is Chriſt, according to the fleſh, that is not incommunicable, is Chriſt, they have the righteouſneſs of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall perfection, whereby he fullfilled the law, imputed to them for their juſtification in the ſight of God, and the indwelling life of it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119669:50"/>working in them inherent righteouſneſſe and ſanctification.</hi>]</p>
               <p>I anwer, none have marriage union with Chriſt but true believers, and ſuch as ſhall be ſaved, for Chriſt the Heavenly bridegrome hateth puting away, when Chriſt the faireſt of ten thouſand, marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any of us Blackmoores, he ſaith as <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. I will betroth thee unto me for ever, yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteouſneſs, and in judgement, and in loving kindneſſe, and in mercyes, thus its upon termes of meere grace and mercy, and therefore this love knot, neither the Law, nor ſin, nor Satan can untye it, to be the Bride, the Lambs wife, is a ſure and certaine eſtate of ſalvation, yea, this Author tells us, that there is ſuch a neere union betweene Chriſt and men in this firſt image, that they are one fleſh, one bread, and one body, if ſo, then if they periſh, Chriſt muſt periſh too, or elſe if he live who is the head, the body muſt live alſo, can the head live when the body is taken from it, I believe great men would be loth to try
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119669:50"/>that experiment, Chriſt perſonall is compleat in himſelfe, Chriſt myſticall is not compleat without the body; and let the Author ſhew us where ever any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the limbs and members of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were cut off and throwne into hell, and he tells us, that they are juſtified and ſanctified by Chriſt, what lack they yet to bring them into a ſaving ſtate? there is union with Chriſt, juſtification and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, who ſhall lay any thing to their charge? God will not, for as this Author confeſſes, they are juſtified in the ſight of God, Chriſt will not, for he hath died for them, and the Author confeſſes, that they and he are one fleſh, and one body, <hi>and did ever any man hate his owne fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, as the Lord the Church, Epheſ.</hi> 5. The Law cannot, for the Author confeſſes, page 118. that the Law hath nothing to ſay againſt theſe men in the firſt Image; here the poore ſinner is acquitted by the Law, and by the Judge of the Court, who then can condemne him, its well this Author is not Judge in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119669:51"/>
               <p>Page 330. <hi>He quotes Zach.</hi> 11.10. <hi>And I took my ſtaffe, even beauty, and cut it aſunder, that I might breake my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which I had made with all the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is this to the purpoſe, doth this prove that men may be one fleſh, one bread, one body with Chriſt, and yet periſh; this Covenant was a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Covenant, which God is ſaid to break, when he did not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, and fight againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and give them reſt round about, as he had done in times paſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſtaffe which God breaks, is called baauty, therefore this Author will needs have it meant of Chriſts beauty and comlineſſe being put upon their ſoules, and that this was taken away, and by breaking of the ſtaffe bands, to be meant the breaking of the marriage union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and them, as if all the Jews had a marriage union with Chriſt; but ver. 14. tells us what is meant by the ſtaff called Bands, <hi>Then I cut aſuuder mine other ſtaffe, even Bands, that I might break the brotherhood between</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Iſrael, not break the marriage union betweene
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119669:51"/>Chriſt and them, but break the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood between <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 363. He ſaith, <hi>Thoſe in the higher image are cleanſed from all filthineſſe of the ſpirit, as well as of the fleſh, which thoſe in the firſt image come ſhort of, having had only a cleanſing or waſhing away of the filth of the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But had not he ſaid before, that there was a heart work in theſe men, and that they were begotten into Gods owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, and likeneſſe, wherein man was at firſt created, if ſo, then they muſt in principle and meaſure be cleanſed from filthineſſe of ſpirit, as well as of fleſh, for the law is ſpirituall, as <hi>Paul</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, <hi>Romans</hi> 7. and reaches to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and thoughts, and intents, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the heart; thus cleaverly can the Author contradict himſelfe when he pleaſeth; and ſo ſometimes he telleth us, they look only to be juſtified in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt their head, and it may be in the ſame page tells us, they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>To conclude this Chapter, after the Author hath ſo cryed up the attainments
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119669:52"/>of men in his firſt image as we have ſeen, when he hath affirmed them to be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the world, Chriſt made their righteouſneſſe in a way of juſtification, and told us how they are one fleſh, one body with Chriſt, knit and married to Chriſt, faithful walkers with Chriſt, he tells us very fairly at laſt.</p>
               <p>Page 361. <hi>That theſe are the devills ſubjects,</hi> though he telleth us in that ſame page, <hi>that they owne themſelves in a profeſſed ſubjection and conformity to the law of God, that is, to what is righteous, holy, and good in its nature, and not onely as it is within themſelves, but as they are made righteous in another,</hi> viz. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly we never thought the devill had ſuch ſubjects, but the Author could not this Gordian knot, if he were ſet about it; for if righteous in Chriſt, in a way of juſtification, and ſanctified by his blood, how are they the devills ſubjects? nay, the Author before had told us, they were Chriſts ſubjects, and a man at the ſame time cannot be Chriſts ſubject, and the devils ſubject, a man is tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119669:52"/>from the power of darkneſſe, when he is tranſlated into the Kingdome of Chriſt. Thus have we examined the Authors notions concerning men in his firſt image, ſo full of contradiction to themſelves and the truth. Now to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his doctrine about men in his higher image, which he maketh a ſaving ſtate, ſhall be the work of the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:119669:53"/>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119669:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Examines the Authors doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his higher Image, which he counts a ſaving ſtate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE tels us, Page 7. <hi>That this higher Image is the communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. (<hi>which Paul wiſhes unto them after the grace they had ſhared in from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, as the common ſalvation,</hi> Jude 3. <hi>and as the fruit of the love of God the Father.</hi>)</p>
               <p>This ſhews the Author to be a Critick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as if a man might have the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and yet be ſhut out for ever from the love of God the Father, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Holy Ghoſt; but what is it to have the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? but to have the pardoning, ſtrengthning, ſanctifying, quickning grace of the Lord Jeſus; and he that hath this to be ſure hath the love of God; he both loveth God, and God loveth him; and this communion of the Holy Ghoſt is an effect of the love of God, and the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who giveth the bleſſed Spirit to thoſe who are partakers of his grace and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to ſanctifie them wholly, comfort
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119669:54"/>them, lead them into all truth, and ſeale them to the day of redemption, and the <hi>common ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Jude</hi> 3. which the Authour quotes is the grace of God which bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all true Believers, Gentiles as well as Jews, called there common, becauſe this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, which is by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, is upon all and unto all them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, whether Jews or Gentiles; for the ſame Lord is rich in mercy to juſtifie and ſave all that believe on him, though they be not Jews by nature but ſinners of the Gentiles; in this reſpect is the grace and righteouſneſs that is in Chriſt, called common ſalvation, and not that it is common to them that are eternally ſaved, and to them that periſh.</p>
               <p>Page 58. <hi>He deſcribes the higher Image to be a beholding of Gods very ſimilitude open and bare faced.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But is this ſaving faith to be beholding Gods very ſimilitude open and bare faced as the Authors phraſe is? Alas! we can have no acceſs to him as an abſolute God with comfort and for ſalvation without relation to a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſeſus, the ſurety of the better Teſtament. <hi>John</hi> 14.6. No man commeth to the father but by him, and he ſaveth them that come to God by him. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.25. that is true ſaving faith, not the ſeeing of Gods ſimilitude open and bare faced; but how much better doth the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119669:54"/>Apoſtle deſcribe faith and ſaving grace. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. where he calleth it <hi>Gods ſhining into our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> There is a very neere approach to God that the Saints ſhall have in glory, and a glorious view of him in the beatifical viſion in glory, but that is not faith, but glorification, not here, but hereafter; as God told <hi>Moſes Exod.</hi> 33. <hi>No man ſhall ſee my face and live.</hi> But bleſſed be the Lord for ever, that he puts us into the <hi>clift of the Rock the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and there we ſee his goodneſſe paſſing before us, and hear him proclaming his name the Lord, the Lord God gratious and abundant in mercy, and that by beleiving in Chriſt we are his children, and that becauſe we are thus his ſons he ſendeth the ſpirit of his ſon into our hearts, whereby we can call him Abba Father; this is unſpeakable comfort to us in our preſent ſtate, that we thus know that we are now the ſons of God, though yet it doth not fully appear to us what we ſhall be, but we know that when he ſhall appear, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, that we ſhall be like him, and ſee him as he is, as 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. and however others pretend to ſee God in his very ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude open and bare faced, we confeſs, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. <hi>that we now ſee but through a glaſs darkly, though we yet expect at that day break of eternal brightneſs in Heaven, to ſee face to face, and know as we are known.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:119669:55"/>
               <p>That which the Author ſaith of ſaving faith, and the higher Image. <hi>p.</hi> 75, 76. we will grant, taking it in a good ſenſe, and with this cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that what he there ſaith is improperly called the newbirth, but rather glorification, and that his expreſſions are too liable to miſtakes, but for quietneſs ſake we will paſs them by, and come to</p>
               <p>Page 139. <hi>He ſaith theſe in the higher Image are under the miniſtery of Chriſts ſecond appear ance wherein he doth not only appear a King of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs conveying a ſeed of righteouſneſs anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that perfection commanded by the Law, but alſo a King of peace conveying a ſeed of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But the Author muſt know that where Chriſt is to any ſoul a King of righteouſneſſe, he is alſo a King of peace; <hi>The peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding;</hi> for its ſweetneſs and comfort is an effect of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo ſaith the Scripture <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30.17. the work of righteouſneſs ſhall be peace (to wit peace with God) &amp; the effect of righteouſneſs (to wit Chriſts righteouſneſs) quietneſs and aſſurance for ever; for as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. being juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith (that is, by Chriſt and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs believed in) we have peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that this is the difference between the firſt Image &amp; the ſecond, that in the firſt, Chrſt is only to the ſoul the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119669:55"/>King of righteouſneſs; and in the other both the King of righteouſneſs and peace is a meer notion; for they are inſeparable; if Chriſt be the one to the ſoule, he muſt of neceſſity be the other; and he is upon this notion too, <hi>pag.</hi> 214. that the higher image forms the heart into the ſubjection of Chriſt, not onely as he is the King of righteouſneſs, but as he is the King of peace: but we have ſeen that theſe two are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the latter the effect of the former.</p>
               <p>Page 224. <hi>He ſaith after effectuall calling that which is the precious ſaving faith of Gods elect (which he counts the higher image) may lie und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in operation from that firſt faith which the ſpiritual ſeed may continue a long time in the ſingle exerciſe of in common with the children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the firſt covenant, as was moſt evident in Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> who after he was effectually called, yet how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and weak did the operation and power of fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> remain in him to the ſuffering of him to fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhamefully as he did!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This we deny, that a man that is a believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his faith may lie undiſtinguiſhed in opera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> from the legall work that men have that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> under the covenant of works; and that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liever, as this author ſaith, may goe on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle exerciſe of legall principles; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> true faith is in any ſoule, that ſoule hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> incumbence and reliance upon Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for life and ſalvation, which no man hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:119669:56"/>der the covenant of works; and this incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bence and reliance upon Chriſt, is an act and operation of true faith, that is diſtinguiſhing from the legall principles of men under the covenant of works; ſo that, the man doth not as this authour ſaith, goe on a great while ſtill in the ſingle exerciſe of the principles of the covenant of works; for if ſo, he is not a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and whereas this Authour ſaith, that this is moſt evident in <hi>Peter,</hi> he is greatly miſtaken; for though his faith might not act when he fell into denying of Chriſt, yet he had before that time acted faith on the blood of Chriſt, and ſo much the authors own words imply, and ſo are a ſufficient anſwer to him. but as the Author jumbles the covenant of works and the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace together in juſtification, ſo doth he in faith and ſanctification; but he muſt know that as ſoon as a man believeth in Chriſt, he obeyes upon principles of faith, and love, and thankful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe in meaſure; and we may as well imagine that the Sunne can be without light, as faith be in the heart without its effects and operations, more or leſſe; and as high as the Authour would ſeem to carry us, the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> will tell him, that ſuch a kind of faith as he here ſpeakes of to be the higher image, is but a dead faith, <hi>James</hi> 2. where he tells us, <hi>Faith without works is dead, a dead faith,</hi> v. 17. That faith that doth not work the ſoule out of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119669:56"/>its ſelfe into Chriſt for juſtification, and doth not work out ſin upon Goſpel principles in ſome meaſure, is a dead faith; if this be the faith that he calls the higher image, its an image in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as the Lord ſaid of thoſe images the people made, that <hi>they have eyes but ſee not, and cares but beare not, and feet but walk not;</hi> and ſo could this Author have his higher image to be that a man for all it goes on in the ſingle exerciſe of legall principles, and ſees not, acts not at all by faith; well, the Lord keep me from ſuch a faith, and give me faith that works by love, and is diſtinguiſhed in operation from a legall work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Authour ſaith in that page and in the next, that when James</hi> 5th <hi>ſaith, Faith without works is dead, the meaning is, that it is dead in point of comfort;</hi> but not only ſo, but it is a dead faith, and the man that hath ſuch a faith is dead in treſpaſſes and ſins; the Author pretends to ſhew us a higher ſtate, and puts us off with a dead faith, a dead image; but this is plain, that he that hath truly believed in Chriſt, faith hath acted and operated in him to an adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Chriſt, to the receiving of Chriſt in his heart, and doth work in him Goſpel-holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſome meaſure; ſo that he that hath true faith and hope in Chriſt, that bleſſed work is doing in his heart, it is begun even <hi>to purifie as he is pure,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:119669:57"/>
               <p>Page 304. <hi>He ſaith, by this faith and higher image man is made no longer able to keep his ſelfiſh power to doe his own will, to ſpeak his own words, or think his own thoughts, or finde his own deſire, or exerciſe his own luſt, to good or evill, as living upon his naturall root.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That after we have true faith in Chriſt, we have yet remainders of corruption, is plain enough by Scripture and all our experiences, that we too much think our own thoughts, and ſpeak our own words; but how commeth it to paſſe that this Authour telleth us that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not luſt to do good or evil as living upon our naturall root? How then ſay I? either the true Saint muſt never ſin, which the Author will not affirm; or elſe he muſt doe it as he liveth in part according to his naturall root the law of our members; for ſo far as we live upon Chriſt, his ſpirit, his love, ſo we ſin not; and ſo far as we live up to the principles of the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e laid in our hearts in the new birth, ſo far we ſin not; and let the Reader examine how this paſſage and the laſt we examined will hold together; he had ſaid before, a man in the higher Image might be like others.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the cleareſt deſcriptions that I can finde him give of his higher Image; and now let the Reader judge, whether this which he calls the higher image be any thing more then the firſt image, ſetting aſide ſome improper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119669:57"/>wherein he confounds the new birth and the glory which follows; for that is the Authors way to apply Scriptures that ſpeak of the future glory of the Saints, thoſe he applies to his higher Image.</p>
               <p>But now let us conſider ſeeing that among all the writers in all ages ſince the Apoſtles there hath none written in this Authors way, unleſs in ſome ſmall matters; and there hath been and yet is a remnant according to the election of grace, how doth the Author mitigate the aſperity of his doctrine as to thoſe who have not known of his notions?</p>
               <p>Page 213. <hi>He tells us that he doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe profeſſors of Chriſt and ſaints of God who have dyed, or yet may dye without ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a higher or better ſtate of acceptation with God then under the firſt Image.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that as much weight as he laies upon his higher Image, he confeſſes it is ſuch a thing that a man may dye without any experience of it, or acknowledg there is any ſuch thing, and yet be ſaved; then I hope the Authors principles will teach him to be charitable to us, and not unſaint us though we will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his higher Image; but alas this is only to claw a little with Profeſſors; for Page 207. <hi>He telleth us that after a man is brought into the firſt</hi> Image <hi>unleſs he yet further abide the trial of fire which is to paſſe upon him, by the ſpirit
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119669:58"/>of judgment and burning of Chriſts ſecond ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, he will not long abide in Sion, but make God ſwear in his wrath that he ſhall never enter into his reſt; let any intelligent</hi> Reader judge how theſe two places of his book agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And yet he tells us</hi> Page 213. <hi>His doctrine is ſo far from ſtraituing or leſning the number of thoſe that are ſaved, that it diſcovers how they may be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d out of the obſervation of viſible profeſsors (among thoſe they exclude as Heathens) and ſo may ſeem to be men in the fleſh, but live according to God in the ſpirit whilſt yet they themſelves may be either without law, or ſo zealous of the law as to fly in the face of</hi> Paul <hi>himſelf, for witneſſing a higher light then they have yet experience of or can bear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſhall not diſpute with this Author whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any are offectually called and ſaved among the heathen who have not the Goſpel preached to them; we will not limit the holy one of Iſrael, who hath mercy on whom he will have mercy; but this we know that faith <hi>ordinarily</hi> comes by hearing, and hearing the word of God preached; for it follows how ſhall they hear without a Preacher? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this is certain, that if they be heathens before effectual calling they are not left ſo, but are juſtified and ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, and have the faith of Gods elect, and they
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119669:58"/>will not fly in the face of <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf for witneſſing a higher life then the firſt covenant; no, but <hi>Paul</hi> and ſuch as bring glad tidings, as the Goſpel or new covenant is, their very feet will be beautiful to them; that a man ſhould have his faith and life in the covenant of grace, and fly in the face of <hi>Paul</hi> for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing ſuch a ſtate to be the true ſtate, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
               <p>But ſtall this Authors doctrine (if he mean as he ſaith) will force him not to unſaint us, though to uſe his own words we ſhould n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his face for talking of his higher Image, which is not more then to fly in <hi>Paul,</hi> face, which yet the Author ſaith a man may do and yet be in the higher Image; this is a ſtrange Image in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that doth ſo con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>radict it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo he ſaith</hi> Page 298. <hi>That he doth not deny but many Saints of God may have dyed without the experience or acknowledgment of this higher Image.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet he makes this higher Image to be faith and the new covenant, and Goſpel; but ſurely that man that doth not acknowledg that the new Covenant, &amp; Goſpel is the onely way of life and ſalvation and that they only that believe on Chriſt ſhall be ſaved, ſurely they are not yet Believers.</p>
               <p>Thus we have taken a ſhort view of this Authors higher Image, and ſetting aſide ſome
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119669:59"/>obſcure expreſſions of glorification, his higher Image is lower then his firſt Image, as may eaſily appear by what hath been ſpoken of that before; and this is the way of men to take us off where we are, but where to fix us next there they are to ſeek, but only the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor tells us its a higher Image, and the glory of the father, ſo the beholding God barefaced, and there is ſpiritual ſenſes, but how it is ſo, he leaveth us where he found us and ſpeaks very little of the higher Image through the book.</p>
               <p>And that we may not leave this Chapter in the Authors dark notions about faith and regeneration, a few words upon that point, leaſt the weak ſhould ſtagger.</p>
               <p>And here we muſt take notice that the holy Ghoſt in Scripture ſets out regeneration by divers expreſſions, ſome of which we ſhall briefly explain.</p>
               <p>For the moſt part Regeneration in the new Teſtament is called <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>believing,</hi> and that is the receiving of Chriſt and reliance upon him alone for righteouſneſſe and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; this faith works by love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the heart, Act.</hi> 15.9. bringeth ſpiritual peace and comfort. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. giveth us <hi>acceſſe with confidence to the father. Eph.</hi> 3.12.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is called the new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eature, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 17. <hi>if any man be in Chriſt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119669:59"/>he is a new creature;</hi> and that phraſe ſhewes us what a great change is wrought in the ſoule at Converſion; old things paſſe away, and all things become new; not only a new head, but a new heart, a new life for juſtification, a new life for ſanctification, new light, new comforts, new defires, new affections, new ends, new aims, new ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is called a <hi>new birth,</hi> as 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5. a <hi>being born of water and of the ſpirit;</hi> to ſhew us how the Spirit doth ſanctifie and purifie the ſoule at converſion, as it is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and by the ſpirit of our God.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is called our <hi>being in Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> the believer is in Chriſt, a member in his body, a branch in this vine; he is in Chriſt cloathed, and wrapt, and folded up in the robes of his righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is ſet out by <hi>Chriſts being in us,</hi> as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Know ye not that Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates?</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 17.23. <hi>I in them, and thou in me;</hi> the true believer liveth in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him; Chriſts being in us ſhewes his acting, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſtrengthening, and ſanctifying of us;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119669:60"/>and ſo it is ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin, and the ſpirit is life becauſe of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes regeneration is ſet out by being <hi>under grace,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. to ſhew that the true believer doth not ſeek life in works of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which he hath done, but freely by grace through the redemption which is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Again, regeneration is ſet out by our being <hi>called into the fellowſhip of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> So 1 Cor. 1.9. <hi>God is faithfull, by whom ye are called into the fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> This ſhews that the true believer is called into fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt in the Fathers love; that the Father loveth them as he hath loved him, <hi>John</hi> 17.23. and the true believer is called into fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt in the annovnting of the Spirit, though yet Chriſt is annointed with that oyle of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above his fellows, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. and the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is called into fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt in his death and ſufferings, that he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of the benefit of that bloody ſacrifice; ſuch a fellowſhip and ſhare he hath in Chriſts ſufferings, that what Chriſt did in ſuffering for his ſins is imputed to him by an act of the free arace of the Pather, as if he himſelfe had done it.</p>
               <p>Again, the believer is called into fellowſhip
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119669:60"/>with Jeſus in perſecution; that he ſuffers with him, is deſpiſed with him; and thus, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, As Chriſt was, ſo are we in this preſent World, without form or comelineſs, of no reputation in the worlds account.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is ſet out by a <hi>planting into the likeneſs of Chriſts death,</hi> Rom. 6.5, 10, 11. Chriſt in that he died, he died unto ſin once; but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God, and we are planted into the likeneſſe of his death, when as <hi>v.</hi> 11. we likewiſe are dead indeed unto ſin, and live unto God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; that as it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 12. ſin doth not reign in our mortal bodies, that we ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof.</p>
               <p>Again, ſometimes Regeneration is ſet out by <hi>putting on the Lord J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. Then it ſhewes how the true believer puts on the rigteouſneſſe of the Lord Jeſus, is willing to be uncloathed of the menſtruous rags of his own righteouſneſſe, that he may be cloathed upon with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Sometimes alſo it is ſet out in Scripture by <hi>comming unto Chriſt, and taking his yoke upon us,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi> to ſhew us how the true believer is ſubmitted and given up to Chriſt, is his ſervant, is under his voke, under his rule and government, is willing to be ruled and governed, and commanded by Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:119669:61"/>whoſe commandements are not grievous.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Regeneration is ſet out by <hi>flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for refuge, to lay hold upon the hope ſet before as</hi> in the Goſpel; ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. to ſhew us that the true believer ſeeth his loſt eſtate without Chriſt, and fleeth unto Chriſt as a City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge from the Avenger of blood; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is mercy, and life, and pardon, and righteouſneſſe tendred to ſinners in the Goſpel, and open proclamation, that whoſoever will may come and take of the water of life freely; and ſorgiveneſſe of ſins, grace, and glory is preached in Chriſts name: this ſoule hath laid hold upon this hope ſet before him, accepted of this grace, accepted of theſe terms of mercy and peaee, and ſo layes down armes againſt Chriſt.</p>
               <p>True Regeneration is a difficult thing, and therefore there is great need of the Seal of the Spirit to ſatisfie us about the work of grace upon our hearts: for there is a counterfeit faith and a counterfeit repentance; there is both an acquired faith, and an infuſed faith; there is a believing, that is only a work of a mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and not the work of the Spirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>With the heart man believeth to righteouſneſse.</hi> It is not enough to aſſent with the underſtanding; its a marvellous difficult thing to find out the difference between that faith that is of a mans own making upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119669:61"/>and illumination, and that faith that is wrought by the ſpirit of God by way of creation and infuſion; and therefore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the world are everlaſtingly cheated and couſened in this matter: But when a man comes to be outed of himſelf, of ſelf-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſelf-ſtrength, and ſelf-wiſedome, and cloſe with Chriſt in a word of grace in a free promiſe, that is the work: To reſt in legal conviction, to reſt upon duties and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, to reſt in amendment of life, to reſt in Notions and head-knowledge of Chriſt and free grace, theſe are falſe reſts; but for the ſoul to be nothing and utterly loſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to apply the blood and righteouſneſs of Chriſt, is a ſafe and ſaving ſtate; for this is the will of the Father that ſent him, <hi>That whoſoever ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:119669:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Treats of Juſtification, and ſhews that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is juſtified by Chriſts blood, and made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, is in a ſaſing ſtate, and ſhall never come into condemation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Doctrine of Juſtification was well cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Luther</hi> the Doctrine of the ſtanding or falling of the Church of God; this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo neceſſary, ſo precious, hath this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor miſerably miſtaken. <hi>Page</hi> 118. <hi>He tels us that men in his firſt image, who are not yet in a ſaſing ſtate, have Chriſt for their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in a way of Juſtification;</hi> and <hi>page</hi> 119. <hi>tells us this Righteouſneſſe and Juſtification the world hath in common with true Believers.</hi> This Doctrine of his is moſt dangerous, and is moſt highly diſhonourable unto Chriſt, making the blood of the Covenant a common and vain thing, that men may be made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate, which this Author doth in ſo many words affirm in that page before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; therefore let us treat a little of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed doctrine of Juſtification. Juſtification is
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119669:62"/>to be conſidered either as an immanent or a tranſient act in God; in the firſt conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is a gracious purpoſe in God from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity not to deal with the Elect according to their ſins, but to abſolve them, and forgive them all their treſpaſſes: Juſtification conſidered as a tranſient act, is Gods juſtifying and abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the poor ſinner in his own conſcience, and actually imputing Chriſts righteouſneſſe to him when he believeth in him that juſtifieth the ungodly; none but thoſe that are eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, are thus juſtified; for men are not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and unjuſtified again, as this Author fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; <hi>Chriſt hath taken away the curſe of the law from them,</hi> Gal. 3.13. Now as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.46. <hi>The ſtrength of ſin is the Law;</hi> the ſtrength and power that ſin hath to caſt any man into hell is from the Law, that the Law is broken, and the Law is not ſatisfied; but now Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for any man taken away the curſe of the Law, ſinne hath no power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that man; it hath no ſtrength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe it; for it hath its power from the Law, and Chriſt hath ſatisfied that, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the end of the Law for righteouſneſſe to every one that believeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. Who can lay any thing to the charge of thoſe that are thus juſtified by Chriſt? the Law cannot; for Chriſt hath ſatisfied the Law, and paid it the uttermoſt farthing; yea God, through the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119669:63"/>righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, is a juſt God, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saviour of them that believe in Chriſt; Chriſt the ſurety of the better Teſtament ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paid the debt, God is juſt in being the juſtifier of him that in Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Juſt to deliver them from going down to the pit, for whom Chriſt hath paid a ranſome:</hi> And ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>For if when we were enemies, we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God by the blood of his Son, much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſaved by his life, by hum living and reigning in Heaven, where be maketh interceſſion for them whom he died for.</hi> And though this Author thinketh that a man may be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, and not be ſaved; yet ſurely <hi>Paul</hi> was of another mind when he counted all things but loſſe and dung that he might win Chriſt, and be found in his righteouſneſſe; and its the firſt time, I think, that ever any man main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this Doctrine, that men men might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, and yet not be in a ſaving ſtate; but what ſaith the Scripture? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> though there be enough in them that deſerveth condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and wrath for ever; yet there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, nor never ſhall be to ſuch, becauſe Chriſt is Jehoſah their righteouſneſſe; his righteouſneſſe covereth all their ſins, for they are found in him, and not in themſelves; but
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119669:63"/>this Author fancies a conditional juſtification, but God juſtifies none but thoſe whom he ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth freely by his grace through the redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption which is in Chriſt Jeſus, whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation for our ſins through faith in his blood; and ſo the Author maketh the offering up the firſt image for the ſecond, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condition of the continuance of juſtification and Chriſts righteouſneſſe; and this ſecond image he often calls faith, and no man hath this righteouſneſſe and juſtification in his own perſon untill he doth truly believe. The death of Chriſt hath both ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and merit in it; not only ſatisfaction, to ſatisfie for all our ſins, to pay our debt, and quit our ſcore with God; but merit, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure both grace and glory, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the blood and righteouſneſſe of Chriſt ſets us in another kind of ſtate then <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocency: And becauſe this Author all along his diſcourſe is telling us that our reparation and ſalvation by Chriſts legal righteouſneſſe is no more laſting then <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, miſtaking the nature of Chriſts obedience, whereby we are made righteous, and not conſidering Chriſts death to be both ſatisfactory and meritorious, and the like, I ſhall endeavour briefly to ſhew the grounds upon which the Believers eſtate by Chriſt is immutable, that he can never come into condemnation, which <hi>Adam</hi> ſtate
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119669:64"/>was not. 1. Negatively, and 2. Poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Negatively, not in regard of any ſtrength that the believer hath which <hi>Adam</hi> had not, I mean the believer in himſelf; but as the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, and kept by the mighty power of God through faith unto ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation; for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in himſelfe is weak; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, in his fleſh dwelleth no good thing; and as thus conſidered, its impoſſible but he ſhould fall, having in him another law, that when he would doe good, evil is preſent with him, as it is at large deſcribed <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>But 2ly. Poſitively, Let us conſider upon what grounds the believer in Chriſts ſtate is immutable that he can never come into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and there are ſeveral reaſons for it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That becauſe the new Covenant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which God deals with the believer, is a covenant of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. Therefore it is of faith, that it might be by grace, to the end the promiſe might be <hi>ſure</hi> to all the ſeed; but thus was not <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, it was not by faith and of grace, and was not therefore <hi>ſure;</hi> but he ſtood upon his own legs, upon his own righteouſneſſe; he was not juſtified and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted righteous freely by grace, and therfore his ſtate was not ſure, but as ſoon as he ſins he dyes, and this is excellently ſet forth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119669:64"/>
                  <hi>Who hath ſaved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace, which was given us in Chriſt Jeſus before the world began. Adam</hi> ſtood upon his own works and obedience; we ſtand upon Gods purpoſe and grace in Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo <hi>Titus</hi> 3 5. <hi>Not by works of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which we ha e done, but by his mercy he hath ſaved us; Adam</hi> ſtood upon the works of righteouſneſſe which he was commanded to doe; we are ſaved by the free grace of God and mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, which mercy of the Lord endureth for ever: <hi>Adams</hi> obedience was uncertain; Chriſts obedience, by which we are made righteous, is certain, his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is everlaſting, the covenant of grace is everlaſting, and the gifts of God therein are without repentance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is taken from the merit of Chriſts death and perfection of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; it is the righteouſneſſe of him that is God and man, which <hi>Adams</hi> was not; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Author undervalues it as if it will not juſtifie us for ever; yet to thoſe who believe, it is precious, by a compact and covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father and Chriſt; it is decreed that by Chriſts obedience to death, even the death of the croſſe, we ſhould be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſaved with an everlaſting ſalvation; and what is this Author, that he ſhould gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119669:65"/>it, and ſay men may be damned for all their being made the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt? but the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. <hi>That Chriſt by one offering hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified;</hi> And this Author ſaith, that men in the firſt image, when yet they are not in a ſaving ſtate, are both juſtified and truly ſanctified; but I would wiſh this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to be more wiſe and wary then to claſh thus with the Scriptures. But let us believe the holy Scriptures, which telleth us that Chriſt hath obtained eternal redemption for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. and he hath obtained redemption for none but it is an eternal redemption; and ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all them that come to God by him;</hi> and this Author ſaith men in the firſt image do come unto God by him, and yet they are not in a ſaving ſtate; but Chriſt ſaveth ſuch to the uttermoſt, that is, perpetually and perfectly, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and for ever; and ſo Chriſt ſaid upon the croſſe, when he had borne our ſins in his own body upon the tree, It is finiſht, the thing is done.</p>
               <p>The third Reaſon is taken from the immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Gods counſel, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>God that cannot lye, hath promiſed and ſworn to keep them for ever that are found in Chriſts righteouſneſse.</hi> And if this will not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie this Author, yet we deſire to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119669:65"/>that he that hath thus promiſed and ſworn by himſelfe, will perform the thing to us; and ſo we have ſtrong conſolation, who have fled for refuge from the curſe of the Law to the hope that is ſet before us of being delivered from the wrath to come, by being made the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, and doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly believe, that by this righteouſneſſe of Chriſt we ſhall be found of him in peace, fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe before the throne of his glory.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Thoſe that are made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in Chriſt, are kept by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power of God unto ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as in a ſtrong guard or garriſon, that the Devil can never take, as he did <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, by craft, when the ſerpent beguiled <hi>Eve;</hi> yea, when Satan deſires to have us that he may winnow us as wheat, Chriſt prayes for us that our faith faile not, but he that hath begun his good work in us, to have our faith and hope in Chriſt, will perform it to the day of Jeſus Chriſt; the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to no man, but by an act of the free grace of the Father; and being ſo freely imputed, its continuance is certain and for ever; God by his mighty power keeps them from drawing back to perdition, keeps them in a way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, and preſerves them to the heavenly Kingdome; eternal life is freely given them by Chriſt, and therefore they ſhall never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119669:66"/>neither ſhall any man be able to pluck th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out of his hands, <hi>John</hi> 10.27, 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Treats more particularly of the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of Grace, and the difference between them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Author, to make his Doctrine more taking, up and down his Book would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Reader, that thoſe that he ſaith are called Orthodox, doe but ſeek their life and righteouſneſſe from the Covenant of Works; and that we may be made the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, and yet be but under the covenant of works: This we have touched before, and here by the grace of God ſhall more particularly treat of. Firſt then, Let us conſider what the Law and Covenant of Works is; It calls for full and perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on our part, with promiſe on Gods part to give life thereupon, and threatning death and damnation to him that diſobeyes, <hi>that the ſoule that ſinneth, it ſhall dye,</hi> as <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>As many as are of the works of the Law are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe; for it is written, Curſed is every one that continueth not in every thing that is
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119669:66"/>written in the Book of the Law to doe it;</hi> which ſhewes us how the Law curſes and condemnes all that are under it upon the leaſt tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſobedience; and therefore as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith here <hi>(being we have all ſinned)</hi> as many of us as are under the Law, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace, are under the curſe; and if under the curſe of the law, then its falſe that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſaith in many places of his Book, that a man may have Chriſt made righteouſneſſe to him in a way of juſtification, and yet be but under the law and covenant of works; for a man cannot at the ſame time be both juſtified and be under the curſe; and we ſee whoever is under the covenant of works, is under the curſe; and ſo conſequently it is a miſtake that the Author holds, that ſuch have Chriſt made righteouſneſſe to them in a way of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. According to the law and covenant of works the leaſt ſin damnes a man; one vaine thought, one idle word brings the vengeance of eternal fire; every diſobedience receiveth ſuch a juſt recompence of reward; therefore ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. <hi>The Law wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth wrath; for where no Law is, there is no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion;</hi> no man under the covenant of works can be juſtified, as this Author imagines; for the law and covenant of works worketh wrath, ſets juſtice againſt us, and makes all the world become guilty before God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>No man
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:119669:67"/>is abſolved under the covenant of works, and hath remiſſion of ſins, but all become guilty before God.</hi> Hence alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6,9. the covenant of works is ſaid to kill; the Goſpel only to make alive; the covenant of works to be the miniſtration of condemnation; the covenant of grace to be the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe; and ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8. Without the law ſin is dead, hath no power to condemn us; <hi>for the ſtrength of ſin is the law;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ver. 11. ſaith by it, to wit the law, ſin ſlew him. <hi>Adam</hi> was the <hi>primus faederatus</hi> in the covenant of works; the Lord Jeſus the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in the covenant of grace: The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was a common perſon in that covenant of works, and ſtood in the room of all mankind; he Broke the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that covenant, and there can be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of that covenant of works, no coming to life that way; that covenant is broken, and ſo all the world become guilty before God; there is no receiving of Chriſt upon the terms of this covenant of works, as this Author ſaies, <hi>page</hi> 118. and in many other places; and in the ſame page ſaith, that we are made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in Chriſt upon the tenour of that covenant; for we have ſeen that by the covenant of works we ſtand upon our own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, not upon Chriſts; we have our life in our own righteouſneſſe, not in Chriſts; it is by the Goſpel, the covenant of grace, that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119669:67"/>any man comes to have Jeſus Chriſt, made of God unto him wiſedom, righteouſneſs, ſanctification and redemption; which Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace comes next to be explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>This Covenant of grace whereof we now ſpeak, was made principally with Chriſt as the common perſon repreſenting all the elect; as the Covenant of works was made with <hi>Adam,</hi> a common perſon repreſenting all mankind; and Chriſt Jeſus is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.8 to be given for a Covenant to the people, the father and Chriſt having ſtruck hands in that Covenant of grace and peace between them both; Now this Covenant of grace is a bleſſed compact and agreement between the father and Chriſt Jeſus, that Chriſts ſoul ſhould be made an offering for our ſins, that he ſhould purge away our ſins by the ſacrifice of himſelf, reconcile us to God by the blood of his Croſſe, and that God would be our God, remember our ſins no more, accept us in him the beloved, juſtifie us, ſanctifie us, beſtow upon us grace and glory, and bleſſe us with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in him; this is that which we count to be the Covenant of grace; and let this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor if he can ſhew that this is but the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works. Our ſtanding in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works depended upon <hi>Adams</hi> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119669:68"/>while he ſtood, we ſtood; when he fell, we fell; our ſtanding in the Covenant of grace depends upon Chriſt, that while he is righteous we are righteous that are found in, him, and ſo Chriſt tells us, <hi>John</hi> 14.19. becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo; he hath performed that commandement, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the father, to lay down his life for his ſheep, and ſo God is reconciled for ever; in the volumn of Gods book it is written of Chriſt, that he ſhould thus do the will of God in bedring the chaſtiſement of our peace in the body prepared for him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his agreement and Covenant with the father to purchaſe eternal life, grace and glory for thoſe whom he had given him, did bear our ſins in his own body upon the tree, was delivered for our offences and roſe again for our juſtification; and his having died thus for our ſins, is as if we had all died, the Law fully ſatisfied. To explain a little what Chriſt according to this bleſſed Covenant of grace hath done for us in his death and ſufferings for our ſins;</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath taken away the curſe of the Law, by being thus made a curſe for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. that the law cannot curſe us or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us for ever; he hath borne the curſe of the Law for us, that the Law hath loſt its ſting in Chriſt: it inflicted its curſe upon Chriſt,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119669:68"/>he by the will of God and his own will ſpontaneouſly yeilded to it, ſo that now the Law can lay nothing to the charge of the believer; becauſe Chriſt hath payed all; thus as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.19. God laid help upon one that was mighty; we could not pay the debt, we could not ſatisfie juſtice, but the Lord hath found out one that was able and willing to do it; that was able to bear the curſe of the Law, and be more then a conquer or; if that the Lord Chriſt hath not ſatisfied the Law to the full, let the Law lay it to his charge; then indeed we had not a perfect righteouſneſs and remiſſion of ſins; but help was laid upon one that was mighty, that upon the Croſſe ſaid it was finiſht, all was pay'd, all the curſe borne, all the wrath ſuffered.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He purged away our ſins by this ſacrifice of himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. there was a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of perſons, he was made ſin for us, who himſelf knew no ſin, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> the ſins that we had committed, he (according to the Covenant between him and the father) is willing to bear, and God laies all our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities upon Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. he hath all our ſins charged upon him, and he purgeth them all away by bearing the puniſhment of them, which makes full ſatisfaction for them all; the Law is ſatisfied either by our performance of what is required, or hearing the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119669:69"/>for not performing, Chriſt he freely ſuffers for our ſins, bears the puniſhment, the juſt for the unjuſt; and ſo God accepting of his ſuffering in our ſtead, according to the agreement between the father and Chriſt, in that behalf we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveneſs of ſins, according to the riches of his grace; and if this Author will call this but a legal righteouſneſs of Chriſts, and will ſeek another to be juſtified by, and have remiſſion of ſins, let him; we know that thus our ſins are purged away for ever, and we can never come into condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but are delivered from going down to the pit, becauſe Chriſt hath thus pay'd our ranſome; the God of all grace according to the Covenant of grace between him and Chriſt, having thus ſet forth Chriſt to be a propitiation for our ſins through faith in his blood; and thus we are juſtified freely by his grace, and all our ſins purged away through this redemption which is in Jeſus Chriſt, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. and no man is juſtified through the redemption which is in Jeſus Chriſt, but he is juſtified freely by grace; not upon the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Covenant of works, as this Author imagines, but upon the tenour of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſt thus dying for us, and in our ſtead, hath obtained an eternal redemption for us,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:119669:69"/>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. not a temporary redemption, and upon the terms of the Covenant of works, as this Author ſuppoſes; Chriſt tells us, <hi>John</hi> 16.10. that his ſpirit ſhall diſcover unto us that there is (perfect and everlaſting) righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in him, becauſe he goeth to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and we ſee him no more, he having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dert aken to expiate and purge away our ſins for ever. If he had not fully and perfectly done it, the father might have ſent him to die again, but that maketh it evident that he had pay'd the utmoſt farthing, in that he goeth to the father and we ſee him no more, but there he ſitteth down at the right hand of God. Thus our redemption in Chriſt is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal redemption, never to come into priſon again; an everlaſting peace he hath made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us by the blood of his Croſſe; his righteouſneſſe and comelineſſe he puts upon us, which preſents us to the father without ſpot or wrinkle or any ſuch thing for ever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Chriſts death is not only ſatisfactory but meritorious, ſo that faith and ſaving grace is Chriſts purchaſe alſo; both grace and glory; we are bleſt with all ſpiritual bleſſings in him; this is the Covenant of grace, and ſurely fitly ſo called; for all in it is meer grace, meer grace that God and Chriſt who had been happy for ever, though we had all periſhed,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119669:70"/>that there ſhould be ſuch bleſſed counſel and Covenant between them, that the ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity ſhould ſuffer for our ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, and that by his ſtripes we ſhould be healed; if ever any thing was grace, this was ſurely, that God the Father ſhould appoint his only begotten ſon to dye for us enemies and ungodly; and that appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is made of this blood of ſprinkling, is rich grace alſo, which is the bleſſing of the New Covenant to give us new hearts; faith and holineſs; is no this bleſſed Covenant truly enough called the Covenant of grace? Iet this Author call it the Covenant of works; we ſee cauſe enough to call it the Covenant of grace, and to cry grace; grace unto it.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen the nature of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of work, and the Covenant of grace, and we ſee there is no juſtification to be had upon the terms of the Covenant of works, (as this Author imagines) but only by the Covenant of grace; but alas this Author not well underſtanding the nature of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works; and the Covenant of grace, jumbles the Covenant of works, and the Covenant of grace together in our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo overthrows the Covenant of grace, as will appear.</p>
               <p>Page 334. <hi>He there ſaith that the Saints for
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119669:70"/>their juſtification have the robes of Chriſts righteouſneſs, as they are worn by Chriſt in his own perſon, made white by himſelf in his own blood, imputed to them for juſtification of his legall righteouſneſs for their juſtification, upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the firſt Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Page</hi> 120. He ſaith the ſpiritual ſeed receive Chriſt not in part only, whereby they have in common with thoſe in the firſt image all the forementioned benefits (<hi>viz.</hi> calling, juſtification and ſanctification, upon the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Covenant of works) but in whole whereby they have over and above that which excels, poſſeſſing and enjoying the riches of both Covenants abſolutely and unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
               <p>From theſe paſſages of the Author it is plain (&amp; indeed hath a perfect analogy with his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that the true believer is juſtified upon the tenour of the Covenant of works as well as a man in the firſt Image; but this is not all his juſtification, but over and above he is juſtified by the robes of Chriſts righteouſneſs, as they are worn by him in his own perſon, imputed to him, as he ſaith; but now the Covenant of works and the Covenant of grace are ſo differing (as we have already diſcovered) that its impoſſible that a man can be juſtified upon the terms and tenour of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119669:71"/>the Covenant of grace and works too; for what ſaith the Scripture? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. <hi>If it be by grace, then it is no more of works; otherwiſe grace is no more grace. But if it be of works, then it is no more grace; otherwiſe work is no more work:</hi> and to be juſtified by faith, and to be juſtified by the Law, and upon the tenour of the Covenant of works, are everywhere in the Scripture rendered inconſiſtent. I ſay not this as if I owned the Authors judgement in that particular, as if what he calls being juſtified upon the tenour of the firſt Covenant, were ſo indeed; for there is no ſuch thing, but whoſoever is juſtified by Chriſt, is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied upon the terms of the Covenant of grace; but to ſhew how the Author maketh a linſey-wooſley buſineſſe of it, and falls into that miſtake according to the tenour of his judgment that he would impoſe upon us, to wit our looking for juſtification by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, whereas we look for our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification only upon the terms and tenour of the Covenant of grace, and think the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the new Covenant ſo entire and perfect, that we look for no juſtification upon the tenour of the Covenant of works to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat it; for as <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Galatians</hi> if they were but circumciſed (to wit with a conceit to adde that to the righteouſneſs of the new Covenant for their juſtification) Chriſt ſhould
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119669:71"/>profit them nothing; no though this Author inſinuates, that thoſe that are called Orthodox are ignorant of the way of juſtification by the Covenant of grace; yet they are not to ſeek for the knowledge of it, nor do not diſtract mens faith as this Author doth, to ſend them firſt to Chriſt for a juſtification upon the tearms and tenour of the Covenant of works, and when they have got that, to ſee that they are not ſafe there, but then they muſt get a juſtification according to the Covenant of grace; no, they do not go about the buſh thus, but hold forth Chriſts righteouſneſs and the Covenant of grace and mercy, directing men to apply the blood of ſprinkling, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt to be their Prieſt to ſave them, their King to rule them, and their Prophet to teach them, and then they have an Ancre for their ſoules both ſure and ſtedfaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:119669:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Takes a general View of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving already particularly ſingled out ſome of the Authors Doctrine, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined it under ſeveral Chapters, I ſhall now give the Reader a more miſcellanious and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral view of this Authors Doctrine: And here we ſhall not oppoſe all that might be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but keep to the end which I propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to my ſelfe, to wit, to deal with thoſe paſſages in the Book that obſcure the Goſpel, and are moſt likely to miſlead or ſtumble-the unwary Reader.</p>
               <p>Page 83. <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Cain <hi>and</hi> Abel <hi>were both for a while worſhippers and ſervants of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to him by Sacrifice in teſtimony of their coming and relying upon the blood of Chriſt;</hi> Cain <hi>without faith, only by a life derived from Chriſt as he is head of the natural man; and he hated</hi> Abel <hi>becauſe he was in the higher I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But what Scripture ſaith, <hi>Cain</hi> was a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God, or had ſuch a life from Chriſt, as the Author ſpeaks of, though he offered ſacrifice as well as <hi>Abel?</hi> yet every one that offereth ſacrifice, is not preſently the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119669:72"/>of God: what though <hi>Cains</hi> mother ſaid ſhe had gotten a man from the Lord? of him are all things that any mother may ſay in a ſenſe of the wickedeſt child; and though he offered ſacrifice, yet it doth not follow (as the Author ſaith) that he relyed upon the blood of Chriſt; a man may doe a hundred times more then that, and yet never rely upon the blood of Chriſt; and if <hi>Cain</hi> did hate his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abel</hi> becauſe he had true faith in Chriſt, and ſo offered up a more acceptable ſacrifice then he: yet it doth not therefore follow that, as the Author ſaith, he was the ſervant of God, and relyed upon the blood of Chriſt, and was in the firſt image; but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that he was not thus; for if he had owned and relyed upon the blood of Chriſt, his ſacrifice would have been accepted as well as <hi>Abels;</hi> for it was by faith and relyance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſts blood, that <hi>Abel</hi> offered a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifice then <hi>Cain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 175. <hi>He ſaith Chriſt brings us to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory the ſame way he came to it himſelf, who was made perfect by ſufferings.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But we are brought to eternal glory by the righteouſneſſe of another imputed to us; but ſo was not Chriſt; we are brought to glory by Chriſts ſufferings, not by our own; let us have a care of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ianiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 175. <hi>He ſaith that every man may keep
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119669:73"/>himſelf from ſuch high provocations for which God ſwears in his wrath they ſhall never enter into his reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God can keep men from ſuch high provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and wilful reſiſtance of him and his wayes, but man cannot keep himſelfe; God can do it by his reſtraining grace, but man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: The way of man is not in himſelfe; it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps; without Chriſt we can doe nothing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> prayed that God would incline his heart to his teſtimonies, and not to covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the very inclination of the heart in man to the wayes of the Lord, is from the Lord, not from our ſelves. Truly, I think even thoſe that are Saints, if the Lord had left them to themſelves, would have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into thoſe high provocations, and wilfull reſiſtance and refuſal of Chriſt, which is the main thing for which he ſwears in his wrath that we ſhall not enter into his reſt: If Saints, and ſuch Saints as <hi>Noah, David, Peter,</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> when left to themſelves did fall ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; then what power is there in other men to keep themſelves from the greateſt ſins? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> one of them, ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.22. <hi>So fooliſh was I and ignorant, I was as a beaſt before thee:</hi> Theſe Saints that fell as they did, would have backſlided and revolted more, even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all evil, were it not that God kept them
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119669:73"/>by his mighty power, and plucked them as firebrands out of the fire; let us not think e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man hath power to keep himſelfe from ſuch high provocations, and wilfull reſiſtance of Chriſt and his grace, but rather admire and be thankfull to him, who is ſo rich in mercy as to keep any of us from the greateſt tranſgreſſion and tranſgreſſions; for we, who as the Scripture telleth us, are not able to think a good thought of our ſelves; are not able to keep our ſelves from the higheſt provocations what are we but an infinite and endleſſe evil? we goe aſtray as ſoon as we are born, are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors from the womb; and if le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to our ſelves, grow worſe and worſe, revolt more and more; and if what the Author ſaith were true, then every man had power to keep himſelfe from unbeliefe; for to be ſure that is one of the higheſt provocations for which God ſwears in his wrath men ſhall not enter into his reſt: And the Author here telleth us, that men may keep themſelves from ſuch provocations; and if they have power to keep themſelves from unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, then conſequently they have power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, &amp; then farewel the diſcriminating grace of God his making us to differ; we know men have their <hi>Wil nots</hi> as wel as their <hi>Cannots;</hi> there is both, they will not, and they cannot; they want will and power; there is both wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and weakneſſe; ſuch vile and miſerable
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119669:74"/>Creatures are we of our ſelves; and let not the Author make our caſe better then is is; let us have a care of Freewill.</p>
               <p>Page 182. and 183. <hi>He ſaith, men may have a feare of God to keep them from ſinning againſt him, and may have an experimental ſenſe of the emptineſse of their good works to juſtifie them, and yet neither be under the Law, nor Believers; and ſo it was with the Centurion, who was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the Law, nor a Believer, until Peter came to him; and this he ſpeaks in reference to thoſe that are uſually called the Heathens.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But though the Heathen have ſuch a light ſet up in their underſtandings, according to which their conſciences accuſe them or excuſe them; yet where doth the Scripture ſay, that the fear of God keeps them from ſinning? nay moſt of them have denied that there is a God, that infinite firſt being of all things; and then they could not through the fear of him be kept from ſinning; and the truth is, no man but the true believer is truly kept from ſinning through a true fear of God; the fear of hell and wrath may be without a true fear of God; the true feare of God is a peculiar benefit of the covenant of grace; and how have the Heathens an experimental ſenſe of the empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their good works to juſtifie them that know not of heaven or hell to come? the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of juſtification before God, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119669:74"/>of ſins is not in all their thoughts: But let us come to the Centurion, and try whether he were thus; and whether he was neither acquainted with the Law, nor was a Believer before <hi>Peter</hi> came to him; and the tenth chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> will reſolve us in theſe things; out of that Chapter we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that <hi>Cornelius</hi> was a Proſelyte in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe and Religion, and ſo might be a true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in Chriſt, though he did not know that Chriſt was already come; and therefore the Lord ſent <hi>Peter</hi> to acquaint him with it; and ſo <hi>ver.</hi> 22. ſhewes us that this <hi>Cornelius</hi> was of good report among all the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and the word which God ſent unto the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> preaching peace by Jeſus Chriſt, that word <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> told <hi>Cornelius he knew, Acts</hi> 10.36, 37. From all which it is plain that <hi>Cornelius</hi> was not to be reckoned among the Heathen; and that he might be a believer in Chriſt before <hi>Peter</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me to him; he might believe in Chriſt as to come, though he might not have light to believe that he was already come, as he was taught after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon.</p>
               <p>Page 183. <hi>He ſaith,</hi> Paul <hi>when he ſaith that he was alive once without the Law,</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>ſhews that he lived in good conſcience in ſuch a ſtate.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he was alive without the law once, his meaning is not that he was not acquainted with the Law that was written in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119669:75"/>Tables of ſtone, but that he was not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſpirituality of the Law, but only made an overly Expoſition of it, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how the Law reached the thoughts and principles of the heart; for otherwiſe <hi>Paul</hi> knew the Law, and was no Heathen in that ſenſe; for he was an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> a <hi>Jew</hi> by father and mother, and circumciſed the eighth day; but it ſhewes how a man may have the outward knowledge of the Law, and yet be without the inward and ſpiritual know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it.</p>
               <p>Page 197. <hi>He ſaith thoſe that hold general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and their oppoſers that goe under the name of Orthodox, doe both bear a true witneſſe and a falſe, one againſt another, and both of them oppoſe and exclude upon divers grounds the true righteous ſeed that live by faith.</hi>]</p>
               <p>But they cannot be both in the right in that diſpute; either Chriſt did die for the whole race of mankind, or he did not; and either there is an election from all eternity of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number to grace and glory, or there is not, and ſo throughout that controverſie; ſo that I ſay they cannot be both in the right in theſe diſputes. Well, but he ſaith they both op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and exclude (though upon divers grounds) the true righteous feed that live by faith. God forbid: But if it be ſo, is not the Author one of them? for I am ſure he holdeth general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119669:75"/>as his book doth ſufficiently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and though thoſe that hold univerſal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, are ſurely miſtaken in that, yet it doth not follow that they and their oppoſers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doe exclude the righteous ſeed that live by faith; for moſt that hold univerſal redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thoſe that oppoſe them, agree in that, to wit, that he that truly believeth in Chriſt, ſhall be ſaved, and no other; many who are miſtaken about the extent of Chriſts death, are yet ſound in the Doctrine of Juſtification.</p>
               <p>Page 198. <hi>He ſaith thoſe that are for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral extent of Chriſts death, finding the truth of their belief expreſſed in the Letter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel (as indeed it is) ſatisfie themſelves in that, and reſt there, thinking it ſufficient to try and judge all men, as they reject or own this literal knowledge of the Goſpel.</hi>]</p>
               <p>I ſhall not mingle ſo many diſputes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or elſe I might undertake to ſhew that general redemption is not expreſſed in the letter of the Goſpel, if by the letter the Author meanes the meaning and mind of the holy Ghoſt; but that hath been ſufficiently witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the worthies of our times; but yet this Author doth not doe well to charge all thoſe of that judgement in general, that they reſt there, and try or judge all men as they reject or own that Doctrine; for though I have known ſome that have been ſo rigid, yet it is
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119669:76"/>not ſo with all; there are thoſe of that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that do not own all to be ſaints that believe general redemption, neither do they diſown others that differ from them in that point; but notwithſtanding their judgement in that particular, they do own or diſown men according to their faith in Chriſt and power of godlineſs; neither do they as the Author ſaith, reſt there, but hold the neceſſity of applying the blood of Chriſt, and of a new birth, though yet ſome of them may take up in notions and opinions, as others do in other opinions; but we uſe to count it great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs to charge all of a judgement with that which ſome being of that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do hold; but if all of that judgement were of this mind, the Author ſhould be of it; for he holdeth univerſal redemption; yet I hope he doth not reſt there, nor own or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject others as they hold or hold not with him in that point; but the Author miſrepreſents others judgements as well as the udgement of thoſe that are for general redemption.</p>
               <p>Page 199. <hi>He tells us thoſe that differ from thoſe that are for general redemption, do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently contradict and deny unto them, moſt clear, certain, and undeniable truths; and all that which they ſay concerning conditional reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, freewil, falling away, and the like, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the children of the firſt Covenant, will
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119669:76"/>find that from the Scriptures which will juſtifie it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author is very confident and profuſe in his accuſation of the Anti-Arminians, and too highly exalts their opinions that are for univerſal redemption, as if they were the very Goſpel, calling their opinions moſt clear, certain, and undeniable truths; but what are their opinions that are moſt clear and undeniable truths? why he ſaith, their opinions of conditional reprobation, freewil, falling away, and the like, as relating to the children of the firſt covenant. Let us hear their opinions, and firſt of conditional re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arminiuns</hi> opinion is, that there is no abſolute and irrevocable but only conditional decree of predeſtination to damnation or ſalvation; and that the number of the elect and reprobate is not ſo certain, but that is may be diminiſhed or augmented; and that the primary cauſe of the decree of reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (not of its execution) is the praeconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and praeviſion of ſin, and not the meer will and pleaſure of God.</p>
               <p>And is their opinion ſuch a plain and moſt undeniable truth? their doctrine is ſuch that notwithſtanding Gods decrees, either to life or death, there might either none have been ſaved or none damned. And according to their
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:119669:77"/>doctrine the grace of election is made voyd; for if it were not Gods free will and pleaſure, that was the primary cauſe of the reprobates reprobation and non-election, but works foreſeen; then conſequently it was not Gods free will and pleaſure that was the cauſe of the elects election, but their works foreſeen; and then fare well that diſcriminating grace and love of God from all eternity; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, we ſtill make ſin the cauſe of damnation; but Gods free pleaſure the cauſe of Gods non-electing and paſſing men by, in his eternal counſels, reſolving to leave them in their ſins; and to condemnation for their ſins.</p>
               <p>Concerning free will, the <hi>Arminians</hi> hold that there is a ſufficient univerſal grace, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon all men, by which they may believe and be ſaved, if they will.</p>
               <p>And is this moſt clear and evident in the Scripture? no the contrary is evident in the Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1. <hi>John</hi> 6.44, 45. <hi>John</hi> 12.38, 39, 40.</p>
               <p>Page 205. <hi>He ſaith that the fleſh of Chriſt may be received and eaten either worthily or unworthily, men not diſtinguiſhing between Chriſts living body, and his crucified body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author if he had pleaſed, might in this caſe have conſidered of the old diſtinction of the Martyrs, of eating and receiving <hi>panem demini</hi> and <hi>panem dominum,</hi> of that which is
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119669:77"/>the ſign and ſacrament, and the thing it ſelf; no man but the true believer eats of the bread of life the Lord Jeſus; for <hi>hic edere eſt credere,</hi> by eating is meant believing; but he ſaith they do not diſtinguiſh between Chriſts living body and crucified body. Alas, the ſame body of Jeſus Chriſt that was crucified, is a living body; for it was impoſſible for that holy one to ſee corruption; and it is not the meer body of Jeſus Chriſt conſidered as living or cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that ſaveth us, as Chriſt telleth us in that caſe, it is the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</p>
               <p>Page 225. <hi>He ſaith</hi> Abraham <hi>was juſtified before God, by that faith wrought out in Chriſt his head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Scripture telleth us, that by Chriſts obedience we are made righteous, and that we are juſtified by his blood; but no where that we are juſtified by the faith that is wrought out in Chriſt; we are juſtified by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs imputed to us, not by the faith that Chriſt had; the Author ſeemeth all along to have many wide miſtakes about the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by which we are juſtified; when the Scripture telleth us we are juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, the meaning is, that we are juſtified by Chriſt believed in, not that we are juſtified by the faith which he had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo he ſaith in the ſame</hi> 225. page, <hi>that
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119669:78"/>faith conſidered as abiding in Chriſt, and not in us, is that which properly juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fieth the believer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Chriſt though in ſome ſenſe he had faith, that is to ſay, he truſted in the father that he would carry him through the work of bearing our ſins, and that he would ſo accept of his bearing the chaſtiſement of our peace, that he would deliver us from going down to the pit, becauſe of the ranſome that he paid, and believed that he ſhould ſee his ſeed, &amp; that the pleaſure of the Lord ſhould proſper in his hands yet he had not ſuch faith as in Scripture is called ſaving and juſtifying faith; for he was no ſinner, that he received another for his righteouſnes. The Author leaving the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Goſpel, runs in vain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural notions in thoſe things.</p>
               <p>Page 291. <hi>He ſaith, that Chriſts Diſciples were called the children of the bride-chamber, and yet then had no higher knowledg of him then in his fle ſhly glory and perfection.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aneth is <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.15. which holdeth forth no ſuch thing, but what a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing there ſhould be in the Diſciples when they were deprived of Chriſts bodily preſence, but that was not a depriving of them of that which the Author calleth the firſt Image; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vay what fleſhly glory and perfection was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt that the Diſciples ſhould know Chriſt only in that? Alas he had no fleſhly
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119669:78"/>glory and perfection, his viſage was marred more then any of the ſons of men. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. never was ſo glorious a perſon ſo obſcured as he was, inſomuch that the people ſaid, is not this the Carpenters ſon? his fleſhly glory and perfection was ſo little, that thoſe which looked only at that, could ſee no form nor comelineſs in him wherefore they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him let the Author have better thoughts of the Diſciples, then that they followed Chriſt and left all for him only for his fleſhly glory and perfection; no, they ſaw him with better eyes, they ſaw him to be Jehovah their righteouſneſs, the only begotten ſon of God full of grace and truth.</p>
               <p>Page 300. <hi>He maketh this the great ſin of thoſe in the firſt Image, that they ſet up the ſons Kingdom in their hearts in competition with and oppoſition to the fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>View the Scriptures a little, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, hath not God; but he that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath both the father and the ſon:</hi> No man hath the ſons King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in his heart, but he hath the fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom there ton; if Chriſt be the ſouls husband, the ſoul will acknowledge God that is Chriſts father to be his father, Chriſts God to be his God; the ſpirit of this ſon being ſent into our hearts makes us willingly and gladly call
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:119669:79"/>God Abba father, <hi>Ga.</hi> 4.6. and ſo we are taught <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.23. <hi>That we ſhould honour the ſon even as we honour the father, and he that honoureth not the ſon honoureth not the father;</hi> and what more plain to our purpoſe then what Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.40. <hi>He that receiveth you, receiveth me; and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that ſent me;</hi> which ſhews us that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever receiveth Chriſt, receiveth the father which ſent him; there is no ſuch thing as a mans receiving of Chriſts kingdom into his heart, in oppoſition to the fathers Kingdom; no man can come to Chriſt and have his Kingdom ſet up in his heart, except the father which hath ſent him draw him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. And this is the will of the father that ſent Chriſt that whoſoever ſeeth the ſon and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in him, ſhould have everlaſting life; this ſheweth us that the father and Chriſt have one will &amp; the ſame will &amp; deſign &amp; Kingdom in the Saints; its the father that ſetteth up Chriſts Kingdom in the heart; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>no man commeth unto me except it were given him of the father, Jo.</hi> 6.65. and ſo <hi>Jo.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Ye neither know me nor my father; if ye had known me, ye ſhould have known my father alſo;</hi> ſee how they go together and ſo Chriſt telleth us, <hi>John</hi> 1479. <hi>He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the father alſo;</hi> I might quote twenty Scriptures more to ſhew the Authors miſtake in this particular, which
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:119669:79"/>is not without danger; for here would ſcare and affright poor ſouls, that they ſet up Chriſts Kingdom in their hearts, in oppoſition to the fathers; but we ſee that where any ſoul receiveth Chriſt, he receiveth the father that ſent him.</p>
               <p>Page 326. <hi>He ſaith that the Diſciples could caſt out thoſe Divels that dwell and acted in hearts unſwept and ungarniſhed, but they could not caſt out that ſort of Divels</hi> Mat. 17.14, to 22. <hi>which delight to reſt in ſwept, cleanſed and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No queſtion but the Divel hath the ſtrongeſt hold in thoſe who have been ſwept and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as it is ſaid <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.43, 44. where the Divel is ſaid to walk thorow the dry places ſeeking reſt and finding none; by thoſe dry places may be meant the true believers that are baptiſed with the holy Ghoſt and with fire, and that had the ſpirit of judgement and of burning; this maketh them dry places; and though the Divel doth in ſome particular temptations prevail upon theſe believers, yet the Lord recovers them again that he can find no reſt there; but thoſe that have only had common grace and enlightnings, and ſo are like houſes ſwept and garniſhed, though the Divel ſeem to have left ſuch men, yet they will find at laſt a repoſſeſſing, and their latter end to be worſe then their beginning; but
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:119669:80"/>what manner of Divels were theſe that are ſpoken of in this 17. <hi>Mat.</hi> that they delighted only (they were ſo cleanly) to dwell in ſwept and garniſhed conſciences? he that was there poſſeſſed, its ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 15. was lunaticke; and have all ſuch men ſwept and garniſhed conſciences? what ground is there for the Author to gather this from hence? no queſtion but the Divels delight to dwell in a man that is in the height of profaneſs and impiety; and where they cannot keep men ſuch, but they are pricked at the heart and convinced of ſin and reform, and yet are ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, and go about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, they are very well content to dwell in ſuch hearts; and the reaſon why they could not caſt out the Divel out of the lunaticke perſon, was becauſe of their unbelief, Chriſt ſaith; and this unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief was not ſuch unbelief as men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for, the not receiving of Chriſt; but the faith of miracles is that which is here ſpoken of; I hope that every one that hath true ſaving faith in Chriſt cannot cure the lonatick, but if they had exerciſed this faith here ſpoken of, they might have cured the lunaticke perſon; The Apoſtles had the faith of miracles, but they did not alwaies act it, not at this time; and to overthrow this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Authors, we find <hi>Luke</hi> 9.1. That
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119669:80"/>the diſciples had power and authority over all Devils.</p>
               <p>Page 333. <hi>He makes the ſinning againſt Chriſt in his ſecond appearance to be the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author leaves out nothing that might appall and agaſh the poor ſoul that won't cloſe with his notions of a higher image and life; and here telleth us this is the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, a grievous ſin indeed, that ſhall never be forgiven in this world, nor in the world to come; we have ſeen before that the Author makes Chriſt in his ſecond appearance to be, namely Chriſt ſhining forth in the glory and naked ſimilitude of God; but where doth the Scripture make this the ſin againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt? the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, is an oppoſing of Chriſt, and the truth knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wilfully, and out of meer malice, that it is not the pleaſure or profit that men find in their wayes, that makes them oppoſe and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt Chriſt and his wayes, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hatred and malice againſt Chriſt; and this is called the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, becauſe that the perſon thus ſinning hath been ſo clearly and fully convinced and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the holy Ghoſt to the contrary of what he is reſolved thus to do unto death; this ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, is not only a falling
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:119669:81"/>in the way; for ſo a Saint may fall but a falling away from Chriſt and the truth; and not every falling away from Chriſt and the truth neither, but ſuch a falling away from Chriſt &amp; the truth that is wilful and meerly of malice and hatred to the truth and Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo if a man fall from Chriſt, and leave him in this manner, as hath been ſaid, whether it be Chriſt in his firſt or ſecond appearance, as the Author di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth, it maketh him guilty of the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt. I haſten towards a concluſion, leſt I ſhould quite tire my ſelfe and the Reader with theſe things; but I cannot paſſe over what our Author ſaith.</p>
               <p>Page 269. <hi>Where expounding</hi> Rev. 17. <hi>where it is ſaid the whore ſitteth upon many waters, and with her the Kings of the earth have committed fornication; he expounds it thus, That by the Kings of the earth, is meant men in the honour and dignitie of the firſt</hi> Adam's <hi>purity and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; that they ſtuck to this whore in oppoſition to Chriſts heavenly appearance.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author might have been pleaſed to have known, that our Expoſitors underſtand that place to be meant of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſuch clear ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments they have for it as he cannot anſwer in haſte; but theſe the Author is pleaſed to reckon under his firſt image; I know indeed they are too much upon images; yet I think they are not in the Authors firſt image; and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:119669:81"/>whereas this Scripture telleth us that the Kings of the earth have committed fornication with this whore of <hi>Babylon;</hi> the Author telleth us, thot by the Kings are meant thoſe that are in the honour and dignity of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s purity and principles: Truly, if there be any ſuch, I am perſwaded they will not meddle with this whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they will not come nigh the door of her houſe; but alas that is not the meaning, there is no need of ſuch an Allegorizing of the place; its plain and clear enough that the Kings of the Earth (literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken) have committed fornication with the whore of <hi>Babylon;</hi> he that hath but glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his eye upon the Surface of Hiſtory, may ſee that, and even of the Kings of this Nation; and how may we take up a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation in this reſpect for the Kings of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Nations of the world at this day, that yet have it not in their hearts to burne that whore with fire!</p>
               <p>Well, but Page 370. <hi>He ſaith, that this whore of Babylon is arayed with purple and ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let colour, with gold, and precious ſtones, and pearls</hi> (which he expounds thus) <hi>many admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excellent ſpiritual gifts received from Chriſt.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that purple, ſcarlet, gold, and pearls, ſets forth the worldly glory and riches of whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of which <hi>Rome</hi> hath abundance,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:119669:82"/>and not many admirable, excellent, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual gifts received from Chriſt; the Author ſpeakes very Emphatically, ſpiritual gifts, and excellent and admirable gifts, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them too; they that have been ſo devout as to goe on P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lgrimage to <hi>Rome,</hi> many of them that have been ingenuous, have confeſſed them to be a cage of unclean birds, &amp; not to have thoſe many excellent admirable ſpiritual gifts; more of thoſe excellent admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gifts may be ſeen in a leather-coat Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, I wis, then in his Holineſſe the Pope; he that goes to <hi>Rome,</hi> may happily ſee abundance of theſe precious ſtones and pearls; they ſay there are very precious ſtones in his Holineſſe triple Crown, and they ſay his Pantofle which he holds out to be kiſſed, hath the picture of the croſſe ſet in pearls and precious ſtones, <hi>ut plenis faucibus crucem Chriſti derideat,</hi> as one ſaith; but I doubt they will ſee few of thoſe many admirable excellent gifts received from Chriſt among them; but I ſee the Author doth not underſtand theſe paſſages of <hi>Rome,</hi> but of thoſe that are in his firſt image; we have ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it already in the third Chapter.</p>
               <p>I ſhall here leave off; ſome things are truth in the Author, and there I cloſe with him; ſome things are of doubtful diſputation; ſome things I have paſt over for brevity ſake; and becauſe the Lord, whoſe truth is precious to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:119669:82"/>him, may call out ſome fitter perſon to deal with that Book, that may examine more and better then I have done, I ſhall ſay no more; I only intended theſe few ſheets for the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the weak of my acquaintance that are or may be of doubtful minds in cheſe matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord eſtabliſh our hearts with grace, make us valiant for the truth, and give us ſtedfaſtneſſe of faith in Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
